<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
                    <lb/>Thus they made <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_no-one">lamentation</emotion> throughout the
                    city; but the Achaeans, when they were come to the ships and the Hellespont,
                    scattered each man to his own ship; howbeit the Myrmidons would <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> nowise
                    suffer to be scattered,<lb/>but spake among his
                    war-loving comrades, saying: "Ye Myrmidons of fleet steeds, my trusty
                        comrades, let us not yet loose our single-hooved horses from their cars, but
                        with horses and chariots let us draw nigh and mourn <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>; for that is
                        the due of the dead.<lb/>Then when we have
                        taken our fill of dire <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">lamenting</emotion>, we will unyoke our horses and sup here all
                        together." So spake he, and they raised the <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">voice of wailing</action> all with
                    one accord, and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> was leader thereof. Then <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">thrice about the corpse they
                    drave their fair-maned steeds</action>, mourning the while; and among them Thetis roused
                    desire of wailing.<lb/>Wetted were the sands
                    and wetted the armour of the warriors with their tears; so mighty a deviser of
                    rout was he for whom they mourned. And among them the son of Peleus was leader
                    in the vehement <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic" >lamentation</emotion>; <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic" >laying his man-slaying hands</action> upon the breast of his
                    comrade: "Hail, I bid thee, O <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, even in the house of
                            <character who="Gods">Hades</character>,<lb/>for even now I am bringing
                        to fulfillment all that aforetime I promised thee: that I would drag <character who="Hector">Hector</character>
                        hither and give him raw unto dogs to devour, and of twelve glorious sons of
                        the Trojans would I cut the throats before thy pyre, in my wrath at thy
                        slaying." He spake, and devised foul entreatment for goodly
                        <character who="Hector">Hector</character>,<lb/>stretching him on his face in
                    the dust before the bier of the son of Menoetius. And they put off, each man of
                    them, their shining harnesses of bronze, and loosed their loud-neighing horses,
                    and themselves sat down beside the ship of the swift-footed son of Aeacus, a
                    countless host; and he made them a funeral feast to satisfy their
                        hearts.<lb/>Many sleek bulls bellowed about
                    the knife, as they were slaughtered, many sheep and bleating goats, and many
                    white-tusked swine, rich with fat, were stretched to singe over the flame of
                    <character who="Gods">Hephaestus</character>; and everywhere about the corpse the blood ran so that one might dip
                    cups therein.<lb/>
                    <lb/>But the prince, the <character epithet="positive" who="Achilles">swiftfooted son of
                    Peleus</character>, was led unto goodly <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character> by the chiefs of the Achaeans, that had
                    much ado to persuade him thereto, so wroth at heart was he for his comrade. But
                    when, as they went, they were come to the hut of <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character>, forthwith they bade
                    clear-voiced heralds<lb/>set upon the fire a
                    great cauldron, if so be they might persuade the son of Peleus to wash from him
                    the bloody gore. But he steadfastly denied them, and swore an oath thereto:
                        "Nay, verily by <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>, that is highest and best of gods, it may not be
                        that water should come nigh my head,<lb/>until such time as I have laid <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character> on the fire, and have heaped him
                        a barrow, and shorn my hair withal, since never more shall a second grief
                        thus reach my heart, while yet I abide among the living. Howbeit for this
                        present let us yield us to the banquet we needs must loathe; but in the
                        morning rouse thou the folk, king of men <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character>,<lb/>to bring wood, and to make ready all that it beseemeth a
                        dead man to have, whenso he goeth beneath the murky darkness, to the end
                        that unwearied fire may burn him quickly from sight, and the host betake it
                        to its tasks."<lb/> So spake he, and
                    they readily hearkened to him and obeyed,<lb/>and speedily making ready each man his meal they supped, nor did thelr hearts
                    lack aught of the equal feast. But when they had put from them the desire of
                    food and drink, they went each man to his hut to take his rest; but the son of
                    Peleus upon the shore of the loud-resounding sea<lb/>lay groaning heavily amid the host of the Myrmidons, in an open
                    space where the waves splashed upon the shore. And when sleep seized him,
                    loosenlng the cares of his heart, being shed in sweetness round about him — for
                    sore weary were his glorious limbs with speeding after <character who="Hector">Hector</character> unto windy
                        Ilios—<lb/>then there came to him the
                    spirit of hapless <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, in all things like his very self, in stature and
                    fair eyes and in voice, and in like raiment was he clad withal; and he stood
                    above <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' head and spake to him, saying:"Thou sleepest, and hast
                        forgotten me, <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>.<lb/>Not in my life
                        wast thou unmindful of me, but now in my death! Bury me with all speed, that
                        I pass within the gates of <character who="Gods">Hades</character>. Afar do the spirits keep me aloof, the
                        phantoms of men that have done with toils, neither suffer they me to join
                        myself to them beyond the River, but vainly I wander through the wide-gated
                        house of Hades.<lb/>And give me thy hand, I
                        pitifully entreat thee, for never more again shall I come back from out of
                        <character who="Gods">Hades</character>, when once ye have given me my due of fire. Never more in life shall
                        we sit apart from our dear comrades and take counsel together, but for me
                        hath loathly fate<lb/>opened its maw, the
                        fate that was appointed me even from my birth. Aye, and thou thyself also,
                        <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> like to the gods, art doomed to be brought low beneath the wall of
                        the waelthy Trojans. And another thing will I speak, and charge thee, if so
                        be thou wilt hearken. Lay not my bones apart from thine, <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, but <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">let
                        them lie together</action>, even as we were reared in your house,<lb/>when Menoetius brought me, being yet a little lad,
                        from Opoeis to your country, by reason of grievous man-slaying, on the day
                        when I slew Amphidamus' son in my folly, though I willed it not, in <emotion type="internal" felt="wrath" appropriate="no" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">wrath</emotion>
                        over the dice. Then the knight Peleus received me into his house<lb/>and reared me with kindly care and named me
                        thy squire; even so let one coffer enfold our bones, a golden coffer with
                        handles twain, the which thy queenly mother gave thee."<lb/> Then in answer spake to him <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, swift of
                        foot:"Wherefore, O head beloved, art thou come hither,<lb/>and thus givest me charge about each thing?
                        Nay, verily I will fulfill thee all, and will hearken even as thou biddest.
                        But, I pray thee, draw thou nigher; though it be but for a little space let
                        us clasp our arms one about the other, and take our fill of dire
                        lamenting." So saying <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">he reached forth with his hands</action>,<lb/>yet clasped him not; but the spirit like a
                    vapour was gone beneath the earth, gibbering faintly. And seized with amazement
                    <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> sprang up, and smote his hands together, and spake a word of
                        <emotion type="internal" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">wailing</emotion>:"Look you now, even in the house of <character who="Gods">Hades</character> is the spirit and
                        phantom somewhat, albeit the mind be not anywise therein;<lb/>for the whole night long hath the spirit of hapless
                        <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character> stood over me, <action intention="negative" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">weeping and wailing</action>, and gave me charge concerning
                        each thing, and was wondrously like his very self." So spake he, and
                    in them all aroused the desire of <emotion type="internal" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_no-one">lament</emotion>, and rosy-fingered Dawn shone forth
                    upon them<lb/>while yet <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">they wailed around the
                    piteous corpse</action>. But the lord <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character> sent forth mules an men from all sides
                    from out the huts to fetch wood and a man of valour watched thereover, even
                    Meriones, squire of kindly Idomeneus. And they went forth bearing in their hands
                    axes for the cutting of wood<lb/>and
                    well-woven ropes, and before them went the mules: and ever upward, downward,
                    sideward, and aslant they fared. But when they were come to the spurs of
                    many-fountained Ida, forthwith they set them to fill high-crested oaks with the
                    long-edged bronze in busy haste and with a mighty crash the trees kept
                        falling.<lb/>Then the Achaeans split the
                    trunks asunder and bound them behind the mules, and these tore up the earth with
                    their feet as they hasted toward the plain through the thick underbrush. And all
                    the woodcutters bare logs; for so were they bidden of Meriones, squire of kindly
                        Idomeneus.<lb/>Then down upon the shore
                    they cast these, man after man, where <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">planned a great barrow</action> for
                    <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character> and for himself. But when on all sides they had cast down the
                    measureless wood, they sate them down there and abode, all in one throng. And
                    <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> straightway bade the war-loving Myrmidons<lb/>gird them about with bronze, and yoke each man his horses to
                    his car. And they arose and did on their armour and mounted their
                    chariots,warriors and charioteers alike. In front fared the men in chariots, and
                    thereafter followed a cloud of footmen, a host past counting and in the midst
                    his comrades bare <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>.<lb/>And as with a
                    garment <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">they wholly covered the corpse with their hair</action> that they shore off and
                    cast thereon; and behind them goodly <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> clasped the head, <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">sorrowing</emotion> the
                    while; for peerless was the comrade whom he was speeding to the house of
                        <character who="Gods">Hades</character>.<lb/> But when they were come to the
                    place that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> had appointed unto them, they set down the dead, and swiftly
                    heaped up for him abundant store of wood.<lb/>Then again swift-footed goodly <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> took other counsel; he took his stand
                    apart from the fire and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">shore off a golden lock</action>, the rich growth whereof he had
                    nursed for the river Spercheüs, and his heart mightily moved, he spake, with a
                    look over the wine-dark sea:"<character who="Gods">Spercheüs</character>, to no purpose did my father Peleus
                        vow to thee<lb/>that when I had come home
                        thither to my dear native land, I would shear my hair to thee and offer a
                        holy hecatomb, and on the selfsame spot would sacrifice fifty rams, males
                        without blemish, into thy waters, where is thy demesne and thy fragrant
                        altar. So vowed that old man, but thou didst not fulfill for him his
                            desire.<lb/>Now, therefore, seeing I
                        go not home to my dear native land, I would fain give unto the warrior
                        <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character> this lock to fare with him." He spake and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">set the lock in
                    the hands of his dear comrade</action>, and in them all aroused the desire of <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_no-one">lament</emotion>. And
                    now would the light of the sun have gone down upon their <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">weeping</action>,<lb/>had not <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> drawn nigh to <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character>'s side
                    and said:"Son of Atreus—for to thy words as to those of none other will
                        the host of the Achaeans give heed— of lamenting they may verily take their
                        fill, but for this present disperse them from the pyre, and bid them make
                        ready their meal; for all things here we to whom the dead is nearest and
                        dearest will take due care;<lb/>and with
                        us let the chieftains also abide."<lb/> Then when the king of men <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character> heard this word, he
                    forthwith dispersed the folk amid the shapely ships, but they that were neareat
                    and dearest to the dead abode there, and heaped up the wood, and made a pyre of
                    an hundred feet this way and that,<lb/>and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">on
                    the topmost part thereof they set the dead man</action>, their hearts <emotion type="internal" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_no-one">sorrow-laden</emotion>. And
                    many goodly sheep and many sleek kine of shambling gait they flayed and dressed
                    before the pyre; and from them all great-souled <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> gathered the fat, and
                    enfolded the dead therein from head to foot, and about him heaped the flayed
                        bodies.<lb/>And thereon he set two-handled
                    jars of honey and oil, leaning them against the bier; and four horses with high
                    arched neeks he cast swiftly upon the pyre, groaning aloud the while. Nine dogs
                    had the prince, that fed beneath his table, and of these did <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> cut the
                    throats of twain, and cast them upon the pyre.<lb/>And twelve valiant sons of the great-souled Trojans slew he
                    with the bronze—and <emotion type="internal" felt="anger" appropriate="yes" direction="at_no-one">grim</emotion> was the work he purposed in his heart and thereto he
                    set the iron might of fire, to range at large. Then he uttered a groan, and
                    called on his dear comrade by name: "Hail, I bid thee, O <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, even
                        in the house of <character who="Gods">Hades</character>,<lb/>for now am I
                        bringing all to pass, which afore-time I promised thee. Twelve valiant sons
                        of the great-souled Trojans, lo all these together with thee the flame
                        devoureth; but <character who="Hector">Hector</character>, son of <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, will I nowise give to the fire to feed
                        upon, but to dogs." So spake he threatening, but with <character who="Hector">Hector</character> might no
                    dogs deal;<lb/>nay, the daughter of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>,
                    <character who="Gods">Aphrodite</character>, kept dogs from him by day alike and by night, and with oil anointed
                    she him, rose-sweet, ambrosial, to the end that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> might not tear him as
                    he dragged him. And over him Phoebus <character who="Gods">Apollo</character> drew a dark cloud from heaven to the
                    plain, and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">covered all the place</action><lb/>whereon
                    the dead man lay, lest ere the time the might of the sun should shrivel his
                    flesh round about on his sinews and limbs.<lb/> Howbeit the pyre of dead <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character> kindled not. Then again did swift footed
                    goodly<character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> take other counsel; he took his stand apart from the pyre, and
                    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">made prayer to the two winds</action>,<lb/>to the North
                    Wind and the West Wind, and promised fair offerings, and full earnestly, as he
                    poured libations from a cup of gold, he besought them to come, to the end that
                    the corpses might speedily blaze with fire, and the wood make haste to be
                    kindled. Then forthwith <character who="Gods">Iris</character> heard his prayer, and hied her with the message to
                    the winds.<lb/>They in the house of the
                    fierce-blowing West Wind were feasting all together at the banquet and <character who="Gods">Iris</character>
                    halted from her running on the threshold of stone. Soon as their eyes beheld
                    her, they all sprang up and called her each one to himself. But she refused to
                    sit, and spake saying:<lb/>"I may not
                        sit, for I must go back unto the streams of Oceanus, unto the land of the
                        Ethiopians, where they are sacrificing hecatombs to the immortals, that I
                        too may share in the sacred feast. But <character who="Gods">Achilles</character> prayeth the North Wind and
                        the noisy West Wind to come, and promiseth them fair offerings, that so ye
                        may <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">rouse the pyre to burn</action> whereon lieth<lb/><character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, for whom all the Achaeans groan aloud."
                    When she had thus departed, and they arose with a wondrous din, driving the
                    clouds tumultuously before them. And swiftly they came to the sea to blow
                    thereon, and the wave swelled<lb/>beneath the
                    shrill blast; and they came to deep-soiled Troyland, and fell upon the pyre, and
                    mightily roared the wordrous blazing fire. So the whole night long as with one
                    blast <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">they beat upon the flame of the pyre</action>, blowing shrill; and the whole night
                    long swift <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, taking a two-handled cup in hand,<lb/><action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">drew wine from a golden howl and poured it upon the earth, and
                    wetted the ground</action>, calling ever upon the spirit of hapless <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>. As a
                    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="familial">father waileth for his son, as he burneth his bones</action>, a son newly wed whose death
                    has brought woe to his hapless parents, even so <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">wailed</action> <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> for his comrade
                    as he burned his bones,<lb/>going heavily
                    about the pyre with ceaseless groaning.<lb/>
                    But at the hour when the star of morning goeth forth to herald light over the
                    face of the earth—the star after which followeth saffron-robed Dawn and
                    spreadeth over the sea—even then grew the burning faint, and the flame thereof
                    died down. And the winds went back again to return to their home<lb/>over the Thracian sea, and it roared with
                    surging flood. Then the <character who="Achilles">son of Peleus</character> withdrew apart from the burning pyre, and
                    laid him down sore-wearied; and sweet sleep leapt upon him. But they that were
                    with the son of Atreus gathered in a throng, and the noise and din of their
                    oncoming aroused him;<lb/>and he sat upright
                    and spake to them saying:"Son of Atreus, and ye other princes of the hosts
                        of Achaea, first quench ye with flaming wine the burning pyre, even all
                        whereon the might of the fire hath come, and thereafter <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">let us gather the
                        bones</action> of <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, Menoetius' son, singling them out well from the
                            rest;<lb/>and easy they are to
                        discern, for he lay in the midst of the pyre, while the others burned apart
                        on the edges thereof, horses and men mingled together. Then let us place the
                        bones in a golden urn wrapped in a double layer of fat until such time as I
                        myself be hidden in <character who="Gods">Hades</character>.<lb/>Howbeit no
                        huge barrow do I bid you rear with toil for him, but such a one only as
                        beseemeth; but in aftertime do ye Achaeans build it broad and high, ye that
                        shall be left amid the benched ships when I am gone." So spake he,
                    and they hearkened to the <character who="Achilles">swift-footed son of Peleus</character>.<lb/>First they quenched with flaming wine the pyre, so far as the
                    flame had come upon it, and the ash had settled deep; and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">with weeping they
                    gathered up the white bones of their gentle comrade into a golden urn, and
                    wrapped them in a double layer of fat, and placing the urn in the hut they
                    covered it with a soft linen cloth</action>.<lb/>Then
                    they traced the compass of the barrow and set forth the foundations thereof
                    round about the pyre, and forthwith they piled the up-piled earth. And when they
                    had piled the barrow, they set them to go back again. But <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> stayed the
                    folk even where they were, and made them to sit in a wide gathering; and from
                    his ships brought forth prizes; cauldrons and tripods<lb/>and horses and mules and strong oxen and fair-girdled women and
                    grey iron.<lb/> For swift charioteers first he
                    set forth goodly prizes, a woman to lead away, one skilled in goodly handiwork,
                    and an eared tripod of two and twenty measures<lb/>for him that should be first; and for the second he appointed a
                    mare of six years, unbroken, with a mule foal in her womb; and for the third he
                    set forth a cauldron untouched of fire, a fair cauldron that held four measures,
                    white even as the first; and for the fourth he appointed two talents of
                        gold;<lb/>and for the fifth a two-handled
                    urn, yet untouched of fire. Then he stood up, and spake among the Argives,
                    saying: "Son of Atreus, and ye other well-greaved Achaeans, for the
                        charioteers these prizes lie waiting in the lists. If for some other's
                        honour we Achaeans were now holding contests,<lb/>surely it were I that should win the first prize, and bear
                        it to my hut; for ye know how far my horses twain surpass in excellence,
                        seeing they are immortal, and it was <character who="Gods">Poseidon</character> that gave them to my father
                        Peleus, and he gave them to me. Howbeit I verily will abide, I and my
                        single-hooved horses,<lb/>so valiant and
                        glorious a charioteer have they lost, and one so kind, who full often would
                        pour upon their manes soft soil when he had washed them in bright water. For
                        him <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">they stand and mourn</action>, and on the ground their manes are trailing, and
                        the twain stand there, grieving at heart.<lb/>But do ye others make yourselves ready throughout the host,
                        whosoever of the Achaeans hath trust in his horses and his jointed
                        car."<lb/> So spake the <character who="Achilles">son of
                    Peleus</character>, and the swift charioteers bestirred them. Upsprang, for the first,
                    Eumelus, king of men, Admetus' dear son, a man well-skilled in
                        horsemanship<lb/>and after him upsprang
                    Tydeus' son, mighty Diomedes, and led beneath the yoke the horses of Tros, even
                    them that on a time he had taken from Aeneas, albeit <character who="Gods">Apollo</character> snatched away
                    Aeneas' self; and after him uprose Atreus' son, fair-haired Menelaus, sprung
                    from <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>, and led beneath the yoke swift steeds, Aethe, <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character>'s mare, and
                    his own horse Podargus.<lb/>The mare had
                    Anchises' son Echepolus given to <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character> without price, to the end that he
                    might not follow him to windy Ilios, but might abide at home and take his joy;
                    for great wealth had <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> given him, and he dwelt in spaclous Sicyon:<lb/>her Menelaus led beneath the yoke, and exceeding
                    fain was she of the race. And fourth Antilochus made ready his fair-maned
                    horses, he the peerless son of Nestor, the king high of heart, the son of
                    Neleus; and bred at Pylos were the swift-footed horses that drew his car. And
                    his father drew nigh and gave counsel<lb/>to
                    him for his profit — a wise man to one that himself had
                        knowledge."Antilochus, for all thou art young, yet have <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> and
                        <character who="Gods">Poseidon</character> loved thee and taught thee all manner of horsemanship; wherefore to
                        teach thee is no great need, for thou knowest well how to wheel about the
                        turning-post; yet are thy horses slowest in the race: therefore I deem there
                        will be sorry work for thee. The horses of the others are swifter, but the
                        men know not how to devise more cunning counsel than thine own self.
                        Wherefore come, dear son, lay thou up in thy mind cunning of every sort, to
                        the end that the prizes escape thee not.<lb/>By cunning, thou knowest, is a woodman far better than by
                        might; by cunning too doth a helmsman on the wine-dark deep guide aright a
                        swift ship that is buffeted by winds; and by cunning doth charioteer prove
                        better than charioteer. <lb/> Another man,
                        trusting in his horses and car,<lb/>heedlessly wheeleth wide to this side and that, and his horses roam over
                        the course, neither keepeth he them in hand; whereas he that hath crafty
                        mind, albeit he drive worse horses, keepeth his eye ever on the turning-post
                        and wheeleth close thereby, neither is unmindful how at the first to force
                        his horses with the oxhide reins,<lb/>but
                        keepeth them ever in hand, and watcheth the man that leadeth him in the
                        race. Now will I tell thee a manifest sign that will not escape thee. There
                        standeth, as it were a fathom's height above the ground, a dry stump,
                        whether of oak or of pine, which rotteth not in the rain, and two white
                        stones on either side<lb/>thereof are
                        firmly set against it at the joinings of the course, and about it is smooth
                        ground for driving. Haply it is a monnment of some man long ago dead, or
                        haply was made the turning-post of a race in days of men of old; and now
                        hath switft-footed goodly <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> appointed it his turningpost. Pressing
                        hard thereon do thou drive close thy chariot and horses, and thyself lean in
                        thy well-plaited<lb/>car a little to the
                        left of the pair, and to the off horse do thou give the goad, calling to him
                        with a shout, and give him rein from thy hand. But to the post let the near
                        horse draw close, that the nave of the well-wrought wheel seem to graze the
                        surface thereof—<lb/>but be thou ware of
                        touching the stone, lest haply thou wound thy horses and wreck thy car; so
                        should there be joy for the rest, but reproach it for thyself. Nay, dear
                        son, be thou wise and on thy guard; for if at the turning-post thou shalt
                        drive past the rest in thy course,<lb/>there is no man that shall catch thee by a burst of speed, neither pass
                        thee by, nay, not though in pursuit he were driving goodlyArion, the swift
                        horse of Adrastus, that was of heavenly stock, or those of Laomedon, the
                        goodly breed of this land." So saying Nestor, son of Neleus, sate him
                    down again in his place,<lb/>when he had told
                    his son the sum of every matter.<lb/> And
                    fifth Meriones made ready his fair-maned horses. Then they mounted their cars,
                    and cast in the lots; and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> shook them, and forth leapt the lot of
                    Nestor's son, Antilochus; after him had the lord Eumelus a place,<lb/>and next to him Atreus' son, Menelaus, famed for
                    his spear, and next to him Meriones drew his place; and last of all the son of
                    Tydeus, albeit far the best, drew a place for his chariot. Then took they their
                    places in a row, and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> shewed them the turning-post afar off in the
                    smooth plain; and thereby he set as an umpire<lb/>godlike Phoenix, his father's follower, that he might mark the
                    running and tell the truth thereof. Then they all at one moment lifted the lash
                    each above his yoke of horses, and smote them with the reins, and called to them
                    with words, full eagerly and forthwith they sped swiftly over the
                        plain<lb/>away from the ships and beneath
                    their breasts the dust arose and stood, as it were a cloud or a whirlwind, and
                    their manes streamed on the blasts of the wind. And the chariots would now
                    course over the bounteous earth, and now again would bound on high; and they
                    that drave<lb/>stood in the cars, and each
                    man's heart was athrob as they strove for victory; and they called every man to
                    his horses, that flew in the dust over the plain. But when now the swift horses
                    were fulfilling the last stretch of the course, back toward the grey sea, then
                    verily was made manifest the worth of each,<lb/>and the pace of their horses was forced to the uttermost. And forthwith the
                    swift-footed mares of the son of Pheres shot to the front, and after them
                    Diomedes' stallions of the breed of Tros; not far behind were they, but close
                    behind, for they seemed ever like to mount upon<lb/>Eumelus' car, and with their breath his back waxed warm and his
                    broad shoulders, for right over him did they lean their heads as they flew
                    along. And now would Tydeus' son have passed him by or left the issue in doubt,
                    had not Phoebus Apollo waxed wroth with him and smitten from his hand the
                    shining lash.<lb/>Then from his eyes ran tears
                    in his <emotion type="internal" felt="wrath" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone">wrath</emotion> for that he saw the mares coursing even far swiftlier still than
                    before, while his own horses were hampered, as running without goad. <lb/>But Athene was not unaware of Apollo's cheating
                    of the son of Tydeus, and right swiftly sped she after the shepherd of the
                        host,<lb/>and gave him back the lash and
                    put strength into his horses. Then in wrath was she gone after the son of
                    Admetus, and the goddess brake the yoke of his steeds, and to his cost the mares
                    swerved to this side and that of the course, and the pole was swung to the
                    earth; and Eumelus himself was hurled from out the car beside the
                        wheel,<lb/>and from his elbows and his
                    mouth and nose the skin was stripped, and his forehead above his brows was
                    bruised; and both his eyes were filled with tears and the flow of his voice was
                    checked. Then Tydeus' son turned his single-hooved horses aside and drave on,
                    darting out far in advance of the rest; for Athene<lb/>put strength in his horses and gave glory to himself. And after
                    him drave the son of Atreus, fair-haired Menelaus. But Antilochus called to the
                    horses of his father:"Go in now, ye twain as well; strain to your utmost
                        speed. With yon steeds verily I nowise bid you strive,<lb/>with the horses of wise-hearted Tydeus to the which
                        Athene hath now given speed and vouchsafed glory to him that driveth them.
                        But the horses of the son of Atreus do ye overtake with speed, and be not
                        outstripped of them, lest shame be shed on you by Aethe that is but a mare.
                        Why are ye outstripped, good steeds?<lb/>For thus will I speak out to you, and verily it shall be brought to pass:
                        no tendance shall there be for you twain with Nestor, the shepherd of the
                        host, but forthwith will he slay you with the sharp bronze, if through your
                        heedlessness we win but a worse prize. Nay, have after them with all speed
                        ye may,<lb/>and this will I myself
                        contrive and plan, that we slip past them in the narrow way; it shall not
                        escape me." So spake he, and they, seized with fear at the rebuke of
                    their master, ran swiftlier on for a little time, and then quickly did
                    Antilochus, staunch in fight, espy a narrow place in the hollow road.<lb/>A rift there was in the ground, where the water,
                    swollen by winter rains, had broken away a part of the road and had hollowed all
                    the place. There drave Menelaus in hope that none other might drive abreast of
                    him. But Antilochus turned aside his single-hooved horses, and drave on outside
                    the track, and followed after him, a little at one side.<lb/>And the son of Atreus was seized with fear, and shouted
                    to Antilochus: "Antilochus, thou art driving recklessly; nay, rein in thy
                        horses! Here is the way straitened, but presently it will be wider for
                        passing; lest haply thou work harm to us both by fouling my
                        car."<lb/> So spake he, but
                    Antilochus drave on even the more hotly,<lb/>and plied the goad, as he were one that heard not. And far is the range of a
                    discus swung from the shoulder, which a young man hurleth, making trial of his
                    strength, even so far ran they on; but the mares of the son of Atreus gave back,
                    for of his own will he forbare to urge them,<lb/>lest haply the single-hooved horses should clash together in
                    the track, and overturn the well-plaited cars, and themselves be hurled in the
                    dust in their eager haste for victory. Then fair-haired Menelaus chid
                    Antilochus, and said:"Antilochus, than thou is none other of mortals more
                            malicious.<lb/>Go, and perdition take
                        thee, since falsely did we Achaeans deem thee wise. Howbeit even so shalt
                        thou not bear off the prize without an oath." So said he, and called to
                    his horses, saying: "Hold not back, I bid you, neither stand ye still with
                        <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_no-one">grief</emotion> at heart. Their feet and knees will grow weary<lb/>before yours, for they both are lacking in
                        youth." So spake be, and they, seized with fear at the rebuke of
                    their master, ran swiftlier on, and quickly came close anigh the others. But the
                    Argives sitting in the place of gathering were gazing at the horses, that flew
                    amid the dust over the plain.<lb/>And the
                    first to mark them was Idomeneus, leader of the Cretans, for he sat without the
                    gathering, the highest of all, in a place of outlook, and when he heard the
                    voice of him that shouted, albeit afar off, he knew it; and he was ware of a
                    horse, shewing clear to view in front, one that was a bay all the rest of him,
                    but on his forehead was<lb/>a white spot round
                    like the moon. And he stood up, and spake among the Argives saying:"My
                        friends, leaders and rulers of the Argives, is it I alone that discern the
                        horses, or do ye as well? Other are they, meseemeth, that be now in
                            front,<lb/>and other is the charioteer
                        that appeareth; and the mares will have come to harm out yonder on the
                        plain, they that were in front on the outward course. For in truth I marked
                        them sweeping first about the turning-post, but now can I nowhere spy them,
                        though mine eyes glance everywhither over the Trojan plain, as I
                            gaze.<lb/>Did the reins haply slip
                        from the charioteer, and was he unable to guide the course aright about the
                        post, and did he fail in the turn? Even there, methinks, must he have been
                        hurled to earth, and have wrecked his car, and the mares must have swerved
                        from the course in wild terror of heart. Howbeit stand ye up also, and look;
                        for myself<lb/>I discern not clearly, but
                        the man seemeth to me to be an Aetolian by race, and is king among the
                        Argives, even the son of horse-taming Tydeus, mighty
                        Diomedes."<lb/> Then shamefully
                    chid him swift Aias, son of Oïleus:"Idomeneus, why art thou a braggart
                        from of old? Nay, still afar off are<lb/>the high-stepping mares speeding over the wide plain. Neither art thou so
                        far the youngest among the Argives, nor do thine eyes look forth from thy
                        head so far the keenliest yet thou ever pratest loudly. It beseemeth thee
                        not to be loud of speech, for here be others better than thou.<lb/>The selfsame mares are in the lead, that led
                        of old, even they of Eumelus, and himself he standeth firmly in the car and
                        holdeth the reins." Then the leader of the Cretans waxed wroth, and
                    spake in answer:"Aias, thou master of railing, witless in counsel, in all
                        things else thou fallest behind the other Argives, for thy mind is
                            stubborn.<lb/>Come now, let us wager a
                        tripod or a cauldron, and as umpire betwixt us twain let us choose Atreus'
                        son <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character>, as to which mares are in the lead — that thou mayst learn by
                        paying the price." So spake he, and forthwith uprose in wrath swift
                    Aias, son of Oïleus, to answer him with angry words;<lb/>and yet furthur would the strife between the twain have gone,
                    had not <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> himself stood up, and spoken, saying:"No longer now, O
                        Aias and Idomeneus, answer ye one another with angry words, with evil words,
                        for that were unseemly. Ye have indignation with another, whoso should act
                            thus.<lb/>Nay, sit ye down in the
                        place of gathering, and watch ye the horses; full soon in their eager haste
                        for victory will they come hither, and then shall ye know, each man of you,
                        the horses of the Argives, which be behind, and which in the lead."
                    So spake he, and Tydeus' son came hard anigh as he drave,<lb/>and with his lash dealt many a stroke down from the
                    shoulder; and his horses leapt on high as they swiftly sped on their way. And
                    ever did flakes of dust smite the charioteer, and his chariot overlaid with gold
                    and tin ran on behind the swift-footed horses, and small trace there
                        was<lb/>of the wheel tires behind in the
                    light dust, as the twain flew speeding on. Then he drew up in the midst of the
                    place of gathering, and in streams the sweat flowed from the necks and chests of
                    the horses to the ground. And Diomedes himself leapt to the ground from his
                    gleaming car,<lb/>and leaned the goad against
                    the yoke. Neither did mighty Sthenelus anywise tarry, but speedily took the
                    prize, and gave to his comrades, high of heart, the woman and the eared tripod
                    to bear away; and himself loosed the horses from beneath the yoke.<lb/> And next after him Antilochus of the stock of
                    Neleus drave his horses,<lb/>for that by
                    guile, and nowise by speed, had he outstripped Menelaus; howbeit even so
                    Menelaus guided his swift horses close behind. Far as a horse is from the wheel,
                    a horse that draweth his master over the plain,and straineth at the car—the tire
                    thereof do the hindmost hairs of his tail touch,<lb/>for it runneth close behind, and but scant space is there
                    between, as he courseth over the wide plain—even by so much was Menelaus behind
                    peerless Antilochus, though at the first he was behind far as a man hurleth the
                    discus; howbeit quickly was he overtaking Antilochus, for the goodly
                        mettle<lb/>of the mare of <character who="Agamemnon">Agamemnon</character>,
                    fair-maned Aethe, waxed ever higher. And if the course had been yet longer for
                    the twain, then had he passed him by, neither left the issue in doubt. But
                    Meriones, valiant squire of Idomeneus, was a spear-cast behind glorious
                        Menelaus,<lb/>for slowest of all were his fair-maned horses, and himself least skilled to drive a chariot
    in the race. And the son of Admetus came in last, behind all the rest, <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">dragging his fair
        chariot</action> and driving his horses before him. And at sight of him <character
        who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly Achilles</character> had <emotion
        type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone"
    >pity</emotion><lb/>and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he
        stood up</action> amid the Argives, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">spake winged words</action>: "Lo, in the last place driveth his
    single-hooved horses the man that is far the best. But come, let us give him a prize, as is
    meet, a prize for the second place; but the first let the son of Tydeus bear away." So spake he,
    and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">they all
        assented</action> even as he bade.<lb/>And now would he have given him the mare —for the
    Achaeans assented thereto —but that Antilochus, son of great-souled Nestor, uprose and answered
        <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles, son of Peleus</character>, to claim
    his due: "<character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, <emotion type="external" felt="wrath"
        appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone">sore wroth shall I be</emotion> with thee if thou
    fulfill this word, for thou art <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">minded to rob me</action> of my prize,<lb/>bethinking thee of this,
    how his chariot and his swift honses came to harm, and himself withal, good man though he be.
    Nay, <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">he should have made
        prayer to the immortals, then had he nowise come in last of all in the race.</action> But if
    so be thou <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone"
        >pitiest him</emotion>, and he be dear to thy heart, lo, in thy hut is great store of gold,
    and bronze is there<lb/>and sheep, aye, and handmaids too, and single-hooved horses. Thereof do
    thou hereafter take and give him even a goodlier prize, or even now forthwith, that the Achaeans
    may applaud thee. But the mare will not yield; for her let any man that will, essay to do battle
    with me by might of hand."<lb/>
    <lb/>So spake he, and <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly
        Achilles</character> smiled, <emotion type="external" felt="relief" appropriate="yes"
        direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">having joy</emotion> in Antilochus, for that
    he was his dear comrade; and he made answer, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">spake to him winged words</action>:"Antilochus, if thou wilt have men
    give to Eumelus some other thing from out my house as a further prize, even this will I
    do.<lb/>I will give him the corselet that I took from Asteropaeus; of bronze is it, and thereon
    is set in circles a casting of bright tin, and it shall be to him a thing of great worth."
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">He spake, and bade his
        dear comrade</action> Automedon bring it from the hut and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he went and brought it</action>,<lb/>and placed it in
    Eumelus' hands and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he
        received it gladly.</action> Then among them uprose also Menelaus, <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">sore vexed at heart, furiously
        wroth at Antilochus; and a herald gave the staff into his hand, and proclaimed silence among
        the Argives; and thereafter spake among them the godlike man:</action>
    <lb/>"Antilochus, thou that aforetime wast wise, what a thing hast thou wrought! Thou hast put
    my skill to shame and hast thwarted my horses, thrusting to the front thine own that were worser
    far. Come now, ye leaders and rulers of the Argives, judge ye aright betwixt us twain, neither
    have regard unto either,<lb/>lest in aftertime some one of the brazen-coated Achaeans shall say:
    ‘Over Antilochus did Menelaus prevail by lies, and depart with the mare, for that his horses
    were worser far, but himself the mightier in worth and in power.’ Nay, but I will myself declare
    the right, and I deem that<lb/>none other of the Danaans shall reproach me, for my judgement
    shall be just. Antilochus, fostered of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>, up, come thou
    hither and, as is the appointed way, stand thou before thy horses and chariot, and take in hand
    the slender lash with which aforetimethou wast wont to drive, and laying thy hand on thy horses
    swear by him that holdeth and shaketh the earth<lb/>that not of thine own will didst thou hinder
    my chariot by guile." <lb/> Then in turn <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">wise Antilochus answered him:</action> "Bear with me, now, for far
    younger am I than thou, king Menelaus, and thou art the elder and the better man. Thou knowest
    of what sort are the transgressions of a man that he is young,<lb/>for hasty is he of purpose
    and but slender is his wit. Wherefore let thy heart be patient; the mare that I have won will I
    give thee of my self. Aye, and if thou shouldst ask some other goodlier thing from out my house,
    forthwith were I fain to give it thee out of hand, rather than all my days be cast out of thy
    heart, thou nurtured of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>,<lb/>and be a sinner in the eyes
    of the gods." So spake the son of great-souled Nestor, and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">led up the mare, and gave her into the hands of
        Menelaus.</action> And <emotion type="internal" felt="relief" appropriate="yes"
        direction="at_someone">his heart was gladdened</emotion> even as the corn when with the dew
    upon the ears it waxeth ripe, what time the fields are bristling.<lb/>In such wise, Menelaus,
    was thy heart gladdened in thy breast. Then <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">he spake winged words unto Antilochos</action>, saying: "Antilochus,
    lo now, I of myself cease from mine anger against thee, since nowise flighty or light of wit
    wast thou of old, albeit now hath thy youth got the better of thy reason.<lb/>Another time seek
    not to outwit thy betters. Verily not soon should another of the Achaeans have persuaded me, but
    thou hast suffered greatly and toiled greatly, thou and thy brave father and thy brother, for my
    sake; wherefore I will hearken to thy prayer, aye,<lb/>and will give unto thee the mare, for all
    she is mine own, to the end that these too may know that my heart is never over-haughty neither
    unbending." He spake, and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"
        >gave the mare unto Nosmon</action>, the comrade of Antilochus, to lead away, and himself
    thereafter <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">took the shining
        cauldron</action>. And <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one"
        >Meriones took up the two talents of gold</action> in the fourth place,<lb/>even as he
    drave; but the fifth prize was left unclaimed, even the two-handled urn. Unto Nestor Achilles
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">gave this</action>,
    bearing it through the gathering of the Argives; and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">he came to his side, and said</action>"Take this
    now, old sire, and let it be treasure for thee, a memorial of Patroclus' burying; for nevermore
    shalt thou behold him<lb/>among the Argives. Lo, I give thee this prize unwon; for not in boxing
    shalt thou contend, neither in wrestling, nor shalt thou enter the lists for the casting of
    javelins, neither run upon thy feet; for now grievous old age weigheth heavy upon thee." <lb/>
    So saying <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">he placed the urn
        in his arms</action>, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">Nestor received it gladly</action>,<lb/>and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">spake, and addressed him with
        winged words</action> :"Aye, verily, my son, all this hast thou spoken aright, for my limbs,
    even my feet, are no more firm, O my friend, as of old, nor do my arms as of old dart out
    lightly from my shoulders on either side. Would that I were young, and my strength were
    firm<lb/>as on the day when the Epeians were burying lord Amarynceus at Buprasium, and his sons
    appointed prizes in honour of the king. Then was there no man that proved himself my peer,
    neither of the Epeians nor of Pylians themselves nor of the great-souled Aetolians. In boxing I
    overcame Clytomedes, son of Enops,<lb/>and in wrestling Ancaeus of Pleuron, who stood up against
    me; Iphiclus I outran in the foot-race, good man though he was; and in casting the spear I
    outthrew Phyleus and Polydorus. In the chariot race alone the twain sons of Actor outstripped me
    by force of numbers crowding their horses to the front, being exceeding jealous for
    victory,<lb/>for that the goodliest prize abode yet there in the lists. Twin brethren were they—
    the one drave with sure hand, drave with sure hand, while the other plied the goad. Thus was I
    on a time, but now let men that be younger face such-like tasks; me it behoveth to yield to
    grievous old age,<lb/>but then was I pre-eminent among warriors. But come, for thy comrade too
    hold thou funeral rites with contests. <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">For this gift, I receive it wlth gladness, and my heart rejoiceth
        that thou rememberest me, thy friend, neither am I forgotten of thee, and the honour
        wherewith it beseemeth that I be honoured among the Achaeans.</action><lb/>And to thee may
    the gods in requital thereof grant grace to satisfy thy heart." So spake he, and <character
        who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">the son of Peleus</character> went his way through the
    great throng of the Achaeans, when he <action direction="at_someone" intention="positive"
        setting="public">had hearkened to all the praise</action> of the son of Neleus. Then set
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he forth prizes</action>
    for grievous boxing. A sturdy mule he brought and tethered in the place of gathering,<lb/>a mule
    of six years, unbroken, the which is hardest of all to break; and for him that should be worsted
    he appointed a two-handled cup. Then he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying: "Son of
    Atreus, and ye other well-greaved Achaeans, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">for these prizes we invite warriors twain, the best there are, to
        lift up their hands and box amain.</action><lb/>Let him to whom <character who="Gods"
        >Apollo</character> shall grant strength to endure, and all the Achaeans have knowledge
    thereof, go his way to his hut leading the sturdy muIe; but he that is worsted shall bear as his
    prize the two-handled cup."<lb/> So spake he, and forthwith <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">uprose a man valiant and
    tall</action>,<lb/>well-skilled in boxing, even Epeius, son of Panopeus; and <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he laid hold of the sturdy mule,
        and spake,</action> saying:"Let him draw nigh, whoso is to bear as his prize the two-handled
    cup : the mule I deem that none other of the Achaeans shall lead away, by worsting me with his
    fists, for I avow me to be the best man.<lb/>Sufficeth it not that I fall short in battle? One
    may not, meseemeth, prove him a man of skill in every work. For thus will I speak, and verily
    this thing shall be brought to pass : <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">utterly will I rend his flesh and crush his bones.</action> Wherefore
    let them that be next of kin abide here in a throng,<lb/>that they may bear him forth when
    worsted by my hands." So spake he, and <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">they all became hushed in silence.</action> Euryalus alone <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">uprose to face him</action>, a
    godlike man, son of king Mecisteus, son of Talaus, who on a time had come to Thebes for the
    burial of Oedipus,<lb/>when he had fallen, and there had worsted all the sons of Cadmus. And
    Tydeus' son, famed for his spear, made Euryalus ready, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">heartening him with words, and much he wished for
        him victory.</action> A girdle first he cast about him, and thereafter gave him well-cut
    thongs of the hide of an ox of the field.<lb/>So the twain, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">when they had girded themselves, stepped into the
        midst of the place of gathering, and lifting their mighty hands on high one against the
        other, fell to, and their hands clashed together in heavy blows. Dread then was the grinding
        of their teeth, and the sweat flowed on every side from off their limbs</action> But upon
    him <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">goodly Epeius
        rushed</action><lb/>as he peered for an opening,and smote him on the cheek, nor after that,
    methinks, did he long stand upright, for even there did <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">his glorious limbs sink beneath him</action>. And as
    when beneath the ripple of the North Wind a fish leapeth up on the tangle-strewn sand of a
    shallow, and then the black wave hideth it, even so <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">leapt up Euryalus when he was smitten</action>. But
    great-souled Epeius<lb/><action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"
        >took him in his hands and set him on his feet, and his dear comrades thronged about him and
        led him through the place of gathering with trailing feet, spitting out clotted blood and
        letting his head hang to one side; and they brought him wandering in his wits and set him
        down in the midst of their company, and themselves went and fetched the two-handled
        cup.</action><lb/>
    <lb/>Then the son of Peleus forthwith <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">ordained in the sight of the Danaans other prizes for a third contest,
        even for toilsome wrestling</action> — for him that should win, a great tripod to stand upon
    the fire, that the Achaeans prized amongst them at the worth of twelve oxen; and for him that
    should be worsted he set in the midst a woman<lb/>of manifold skill in handiwork, and they
    prized her at the worth of four oxen. And <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">he stood up and spake among the Argives saying</action>:"Up now, ye
    twain that will make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">thereat arose great Telamonian
        Aias, and up stood Odysseus of many wiles, he of guileful mind.</action><lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">Then the twain, when they had
        girded themselves, stepped into the midst of the place of gathering, and laid hold each of
        the other in close grip with their mighty hands, even as the gable-rafters of a high house,
        which some famous craftsman joineth together, that he may have shelter from the might of the
        winds.</action>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">And their backs creaked
        beneath the violent tugging of bold hands</action>,<lb/><action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">and the sweat flowed down in streams; and many a
        weal, red with blood, sprang up along their ribs and shoulders; and ever they strove amain
        for victory, to win the fashioned tripod.</action> Neither might Odysseus avail to trip Aias
    and throw him to the ground,<lb/>nor Aias him, for <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">the mighty strength of Odysseus held firm.</action> But when at the
    last they were like to weary the well-greaved Achaeans, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">then unto Odysseus spake great Telamonian Aias,
        saying</action>:"Zeus-born, son of Laertes, Odysseus of many wiles, lift thou me, or let me
    lift thee; but the issue shall rest with <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>." <lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">He spake, and lifted him; but
        Odysseus forgat not his guile. He smote with a sure blow the hollow of Aias' knee from
        behind, and loosed his limbs, so that he was thrown backward, and Odysseus fell upon his
        chest; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with wonder.</action> Then in his turn
    the much-enduring goodly Odysseus essayed to lift,<lb/>and moved him a little from the ground,
    but lifted him not, howbeit he crooked his knee within that of Aias, <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">and upon the ground the twain
        fell one hard by the other, and were befouled with dust. And now would they have sprung up
        again for the third time and have wrestled,</action> but that <character who="Achilles"
        >Achilles</character> himself <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">uprose, and held them back</action>:<lb/>"No longer strain ye now,
    neither be worn with pain. Victory is with you both; take then equa1 prizes and go your ways,
    that other Achaeans too may strive." So spake he, and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">they readily hearkened to him and obeyed, and wiping
        from their bodies the dust they put upon them their tunics.</action><lb/>
    <lb/>Then <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">the son of Peleus</character> straightway
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">set forth other
        prizes</action> for fleetness of foot: a mixingbowl of silver, richly wrought; six measures
    it held, and in beauty it was far the goodliest in all the earth, seeing that Sidonians, well
    skilled in deft handiwork, had wrought it cunningly, and men of the Phoenicians brought it over
    the murky deep, and landed it in harbour,<lb/>and gave it as a gift to Thoas; and as a ransom
    for Lycaon, son of <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, Jason's son Euneos gave it to the
    warrior <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>. This bowl did <character
        who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one" relationship="romantic">set
        forth as a prize in honour of his comrade</action>, even for him whoso should prove fleetest
    in speed of foot.<lb/>For the second again <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">he set an ox great and rich with fat; and a half-talent in gold he
        appointed for the last.</action> And <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">he stood up, and spake among the Argives saying</action>: "Up now, ye
    that will make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">forthwith uprose</action> swift Aias, son of
    Oïleus,<lb/>and Odysseus of many wiles, and after them Antilochus, Nestor's son, for he
    surpassed all the youths in swiftness of foot. <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">Then took they their places in a row, and Achilles showed them the
        goal, and a course was marked out for them from the turning-point.</action> Then speedily
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the son of Oïleus forged
        to the front, and close after him sped goodly Odysseus</action>;<lb/>close as is the
    weaving-rod to the breast of a fair-girdled woman, when she deftly draweth it in her hands,
    pulling the spool past the warp, and holdeth the rod nigh to her breast; even so close behind
    ran Odysseus,<lb/><action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">and his
        feet trod in the footsteps of Aias or ever the dust had settled therein, and down upon his
        head beat the breath of goodly Odysseus, as he ran ever swiftly on; and all the Achaeans
        shouted to further him as he struggled for victory, and called to him as he strained to the
        utmost.</action> But when now they were running the last part of the course, straightway
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">Odysseus made prayer in
        his heart</action> to <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">flashing-eyed
        Athene</character>:<lb/>"Hear me, goddess, and come a goodly helper to my feet." So spake he
    in prayer, and <character who="Gods">Pallas Athene</character> heard him, and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">made his limbs light, his feet
        and his hands above</action>. But when they were now about to dart forth to win the prize,
    then <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">Aias slipped as he
        ran</action>—for <character who="Gods">Athene</character>
    <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">hampered
    him</action>—<lb/>where was strewn the filth from the slaying of the loud bellowing bulls that
        <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed Achilles</character> had slain in
    honour of <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>; and with <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the filth of the bulls were his
        mouth and nostrils filled</action>. So then much-enduring, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">goodly Odysseus took up the bowl, seeing he came in
        the first</action>, and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one"
        >glorious Aias took the ox.</action><lb/>And <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">he stood holding in his hands the horn of the ox of the field, spewing
        forth the filth</action>; and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">he spake among the Argives</action>: "Out upon it, lo, <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">the goddess hampered me in my
        running</action>, she that standeth ever by Odysseus' side like a mother, and helpeth
    him."<lb/> So spake he, but <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"
        >they all laughed merrily at him.</action><lb/>Then <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">Antilochus bare away the last prize, smiling the
        while, and spake among the Argives, saying</action>: "Among you all that know it well, will
    I declare, my friends, that even to this day <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">the immortals shew honour to older men.</action> For Aias is but a
    little older than I,<lb/>whereas Odysseus is of an earlier generation and of earlier men—a green
    old age is his, men say—yet hard were he for any other Achaean to contend with in running, save
    only for Achilles." So spake he, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">gave glory</action> to <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive"
        >the son of Peleus, swift of foot.</character> And <character who="Achilles"
        >Achilles</character> made answer, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">and spake to him, saying</action>:<lb/>"Antilochus, not in vain shall
    thy word of praise be spoken; nay, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">I will add to thy prize a half-talent of gold</action>." So saying,
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">he set it in his hands,
        and Antilochus received it gladly</action>. But <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral"
        >the son of Peleus</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">brought and set in the
        place</action> of gathering a far-shadowing spear, and therewith a shield and
    helmet,<lb/>the battlegear of Sarpedon, that <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>
    stripped from him; and he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying:"To win these prizes
    invite we warriors twain, the best there are, to clothe them in their armour and take bronze
    that cleaveth the flesh, and so make trial each of the other before the host.<lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">Whoso of the twain shall first
        reach the other's fair flesh, and touch the inward parts through armour and dark blood, to
        him will I give this silver-studded sword</action>—a goodly Thracian sword which I took from
    Asteropaeus; and these arms let the twain bear away to hold in common;<lb/>and a goodly banquet
    shall we set before them in our huts." So spake he, and thereat <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">arose great Telamonian Aias, and up rose the son of
        Tydeus, stalwart Diomedes</action>. So <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">when they had armed them on either side of the throng, into the midst
        strode the twain, eager for battle</action>,<lb/>glaring terribly; and amazement held all
    the Achaeans. But when they were come near as <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">they advance done against the other, thrice they set upon each other,
        and thrice they clashed together</action>. Then <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">Aias thrust upon the shield</action>, that was
    well-balanced upon every side, but reached not the flesh, for the corselet within kept off the
    spear.<lb/>But Tydeus' son over the great shield <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">sought ever to reach the neck with the point of his shining
        spear</action>, Then verily the Achaeans, seized with fear for Aias, <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">bade them cease and take up
        equal prizes</action>. Howbeit to Tydeus' son the warrior gave the great sword,<lb/>bringing
    it with its scabbard and its well-cut baldric.<lb/> Then the <character who="Achilles"
        epithet="neutral">son of Peleus</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">set forth a mass of
        rough-cast iron</action>, which of old the mighty strength of Eëtion was wont to hurl; but
    him had <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed goodly Achilles</character>
    slain, and bare this away on his ships with his other possessions.<lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">And he stood up, and spake
        among the Argives</action>, saying :"Up now, ye that will make essay likewise in this
    contest. Though his rich fields lie very far remote, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the winner hereof will have it five revolving years
        to serve his need</action>; for not through lack of iron will his shepherd or
    ploughman<lb/>fare to the city; nay, this will supply them." So spake he, and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">thereat arose Polypoetes,
        staunch in fight, and the mighty strength of godlike Leonteus, and Aias, son of Telamon, and
        goodly Epeius.</action> Then <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">they took their places in order</action>, and goodly Epeius grasped
    the mass,<lb/>and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">whirled
        and flung it</action>; and <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">all the Achaeans laughed aloud</action> thereat. Then in turn
    Leonteus, scion of Ares,<action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">
        made a cast</action>; and thirdly great Telamonian Aias <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">hurled it from his strong hand, and sent it past the
        marks of all</action>. But when Polypoetes, staunch in fight,<lb/>grasped the mass, far as a
    herdsman flings his crook, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">it flieth whirling over the herds of kine, even so far cast he it
        beyond all the gathering; and the folk shouted aloud. And the comrades of strong Polypoetes
        rose up and bare to the hollow ships the prize of the king.</action>
    <lb/>Then <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">for the archers he
        set forth as a prize dark iron—ten double axes laid he down, and ten single; and he set up
        the mast of a dark-prowed ship far off in the sands, and with a slender cord made fast
        thereto by the foot a timorous dove, and bade shoot thereat.</action><lb/>"<action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">Whoso shall hit the timorous
        dove let him take up all the double axes and bear them home, and whoso shall hit the cord,
        albeit he miss the bird: lo, his is the worser shot; he shall bear as his prize the single
        axes.</action>"<lb/> So spake he, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">there arose</action> the might of the prince Teucer,<lb/>and Meriones
    the valiant squire of Idomeneus. <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">Then took they the lots and shook them in a helmet of bronze, and
        Teucer drew by lot the first place. Forthwith he let fly an arrow with might, howbeit he
        vowed not that he would sacrifice to the king a glorious hecatomb of firstling
        lambs.</action><lb/>So he <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one"> missed the bird</action>, for <character who="Gods"
        >Apollo</character>
    <emotion appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" felt="anger" relationship="neutral"
        type="external">grudged him</emotion> that, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">but hit the cord beside its foot wherewith the bird was tied, and
        clean away the bitter arrow cut the cord. Then the dove darted skyward, and the cord hung
        loose toward earth;</action> and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">the Achaeans shouted aloud</action>.<lb/>But Meriones <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">speedily snatched the bow from
        Teucer's hand—an arrow had he long been holding while Teucer aimed</action>—and <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">vowed forthwith that he would
        sacrifice</action> to <character who="Gods">Apollo</character> that smiteth afar a glorious
    hecatomb of firstling lambs. High up beneath the cloud <action intention="negative"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he spied the timorous dove</action>;<lb/>there as she
    circled round <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he struck her
        in the midst beneath the wing, and clean through passed the shaft, and fell again and fixed
        itself in the ground before the foot of Meriones; but the dove, lighting on the mast of the
        dark-prowed ship, hung down her head, and her thick plumage drooped.</action><lb/>Swiftly
        <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the life fled from her
        limbs, and she fell far from the mast; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with
        wonder.</action>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">And Meriones took up all ten
        double axes, and Teucer bare the single to the hollow ships.</action> Then <character
        who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">the son of Peleus</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">brought and set in the place
        of gathering a far-shadowing spear</action><lb/>and a cauldron, that the fire had not yet
    touched, of an ox's worth, embossed with flowers; and men that were hurlers of javelins arose.
    Up rose the son of Atreus, <character who="Agamemnon" epithet="positive">wide-ruling
        Agamemnon</character> and Meriones, the valiant squire of Idomeneus. But among them spake
        <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly
    Achilles</character>:<lb/>"Son of Atreus, we know how far thou excellest all, and how far thou
    art the best in might and in the casting of the spear; nay, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">take thou this prize and go thy way to the hollow
        ships; but the spear let us give to the warrior Meriones,</action> if thy heart consenteth
    thereto: so at least would I have it:" <lb/>So spake he, and <character who="Agamemnon"
        epithet="positive">the king of men, Agamemnon</character>, failed not to hearken. Then
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">to Meriones he gave the
        spear of bronze, but the warrior handed to the herald Talthybius the beauteous
        prize.</action>
    <!-- BOOK 24 START -->
    <lb/><action intention="positive" direction="at_no-one" setting="public">Then was the gathering
        broken up, and the folk scattered, each man to go to his own ship. The rest bethought them of
        supper and of sweet sleep, to take their fill thereof</action>; but <character who="Achilles"
            >Achilles</character>
    <action intention="negative" direction="at_no-one" setting="private" relationship="romantic">wept,
        ever remembering his dear comrade</action>, neither might sleep,<lb/>that mastereth all, lay hold
    of him, but he turned him ever to this side or to that, <emotion direction="at_someone"
        appropriate="yes" felt="lament" relationship="romantic" type="internal">yearning for the man-hood
        and valorous might</emotion> of <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, thinking on all
    he had wrought with him and all the woes he had borne, passing though wars of men and the grievous
    waves. Thinking thereon <action intention="negative" direction="at_no-one" setting="private">he
        would shed big tears</action>,<lb/>lying now upon his side, now upon his back, and now upon his
    face; and then again <action intention="negative" direction="at_no-one" setting="private">he would
        rise upon his feet and roam distraught along the shore of the sea.</action> Neither would he fail
    to mark the Dawn, as she shone over the sea and the sea-beaches, but would yoke beneath the car his
    swift horses,<lb/>and bind <character who="Hector">Hector</character>
    <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public">behind the chariot to drag him
        withal; and when he had haled him thrice about the barrow of the dead son of Menoetius</action>,
    he would rest again in his hut, but would leave <character who="Hector">Hector</character>
    outstretched on his face in the dust. Howbeit <character who="Gods">Apollo</character>
    <action intention="positive" direction="at_someone" setting="public">kept all defacement from his
        flesh, pitying the warrior</action><lb/>even in death, and with the golden aegis he covered him
    wholly, that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> might not tear his body as he dragged
    him.<lb/> Thus <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> in his <emotion type="external"
        relationship="enemies" appropriate="yes" felt="wrath" direction="at_someone">fury</emotion> did
    foul despite unto <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">goodly Hector</character>; but the
    blessed gods had pity on him as they beheld him, and bestirred the keen-sighted Argeiphontes to
    steal away the corpse.<lb/>And the thing was pleasing unto all the rest, yet not unto <character
        who="Gods">Hera</character> or <character who="Gods">Poseidon</character> or the flashing-eyed
    maiden, but they continued even as when at the first sacred Ilios became hateful in their eyes and
    <character who="Priam">Priam</character> and his folk, by reason of the sin of Alexander, for that
    he put reproach upon those goddesses when they came to his steading,<lb/><action
        intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public">and gave precedence to her who
        furthered his fatal lustfulness.</action> But when at length the twelfth morn thereafter was come,
    then <action intention="positive" direction="at_someone" setting="public">among the immortals
        spake</action>
    <character who="Gods">Phoebus Apollo</character>:"Cruel are ye, O ye gods, and workers of bane.
    Hath <character who="Hector">Hector</character> then never burned for you thighs of bulls and goats
    without blemish?<lb/>Him now have ye not the heart to save, a corpse though he be, for his wife to
    look upon and his mother and his child, and his father <character who="Priam">Priam</character> and
    his people, who would forthwith burn him in the fire and pay him funeral rites. Nay, it is
    <character who="Achilles" epithet="negative">the ruthless Achilles</character>, O ye gods, that ye
    are fain to succour,<lb/><emotion direction="at_someone" felt="anger" appropriate="yes"
        relationship="neutral" type="external">him whose mind is nowise right, neither the purpose in his
        breast one that may be bent; but his heart is set on cruelty,</emotion> even as a lion that at the
    bidding of his great might and lordly spirit goeth forth against the flocks of men to win him a
    feast; even so hath <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> lost all pity, neither is shame
    in his heart,<lb/>the which harmeth men greatly and profiteth them withal. Lo, it may be that a man
    hath lost one dearer even than was this—a brother, that the selfsame mother bare, or haply a son;
    yet verily when he hath wept and wailed for him he maketh an end; for an enduring soul have the
    Fates given unto men.<lb/>But this man, when he hath reft <character who="Hector"
        epithet="positive">goodly Hector</character> of life, bindeth him behind his chariot and draggeth
    him about the barrow of his dear comrade; in sooth neither honour nor profit shall he have
    therefrom. Let him beware lest we wax wroth with him, good man though he be; for lo, in his fury he
    doth foul despite unto senseless clay." <lb/>Then <emotion type="external" relationship="familial"
        appropriate="yes" felt="anger" direction="at_someone">stirred to anger</emotion> spake to him
    <character epithet="neutral" who="Gods"> white-armed Hera</character>:"Even this might be as thou
    sayest, Lord of the silver bow, if indeed ye gods will vouchsafe like honour to <character
        who="Achilles">Achilles</character> and to <character who="Hector">Hector</character>. <character
            who="Hector">Hector</character> is but mortal and was suckled at a woman's breast, but <character
                who="Achilles">Achilles</character> is the child of a goddess that I mine own self<lb/>fostered
    and reared, and gave to a warrior to be his wife, even to Peleus, who was heartily dear to the
    immortals. And all of you, O ye gods, came to her marriage, and among them thyself too didst sit at
    the feast, thy lyre in thy hand, O thou friend of evil-doers, faithless ever."<lb/> Then <character
        who="Gods" epithet="neutral">Zeus, the cloud-gatherer,</character>
    <action direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic" setting="public" intention="negative"
        >answered her</action>, and said:<lb/>"<character who="Gods">Hera</character>, be not thou utterly
    wroth against the gods; the honour of these twain shall not be as one; howbeit <character
        who="Hector">Hector</character> too was dearest to the gods of all mortals that are in Ilios. So
    was he to me at least, for nowise failed he of acceptable gifts. For never was my altar in lack of
    the equal feast,<lb/>the drink-offiering and the savour of burnt-offering, even the worship that is
    our due. Howbeit of the stealing away of bold <character who="Hector">Hector</character> will we
    naught; it may not be but that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> would be ware
    thereof; for verily his mother cometh ever to his side alike by night and day. But I would that one
    of the gods would call Thetis to come unto me,<lb/>that I may speak to her a word of wisdom, to the
    end that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> may accept gifts from <character
        who="Priam">Priam</character>, and give <character who="Hector">Hector</character> back." So spake
    he, and storm-footed Iris <action direction="at_no-one" intention="positive" setting="public"
        >hasted to bear his message</action>, and midway between Samos and rugged Imbros she leapt into
    the dark sea, and the waters sounded loud above her.<lb/>Down sped she to the depths hike a plummet
    of lead, the which, set upon the horn of an ox of the field, goeth down bearing death to the
    ravenous fishes. And she found Thetis in the hollow cave, and round about her other goddesses of
    the sea sat in a throng, and she in their midst<lb/>was wailing for the fate of her peerless son,
    who to her sorrow was to perish in deep-soiled Troy, far from his native land. And swift-footed
    Iris drew near, and spake to her:"Rouse thee, 0 Thetis; <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>,
    whose counsels are everlasting, calleth thee." Then spake in answer Thetis, the silver-footed
    goddess:<lb/>"Wherefore summoneth me that mighty god? I have shame to mingle in the company of the
    immortals, seeing I have measurehess griefs at heart. Howbeit I will go, neither shall his word be
    vain, whatsoever he shall speak."<lb/> So saying, the fair goddess took a dark-hued veil, than
    which was no raiment more black,<lb/>and<action direction="at_no-one" intention="positive"
        setting="public"> set out to go, and before her wind-footed swift Iris led the way</action>; and
    about them the surge of the sea parted asunder. And when they had stepped forth upon the beach they
    sped unto heaven; and they found the son of Cronos, whose voice is borne afar, and around him sat
    gathered together all the other blessed gods that are for ever.<lb/>Then she sate her down beside
    father <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>, and <character who="Gods">Athene</character> gave
    place. And <character who="Gods">Hera</character> set in her hand a fair golden cup, and spake
    words of cheer.; and Thetis drank, and gave back the cup. Then among them <action
        direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">the father of men and gods was first
        to speak</action>:"Thou art come to Olympus, 0, goddess Thetis,<lb/>for all thy sorrow, though
    thou hast comfortless grief at heart; I know it of myself; yet even so will I tell thee wherefore I
    called thee hither. For nine days' space hath strife arisen among the immortals as touching the
    corpse of <character who="Hector">Hector</character> and <character who="Achilles"
        epithet="negative">Achilles, sacker of cities</character>. They are for bestirring the
    keen-sighted Argeiphontes to steal the body away,<lb/>yet herein do I accord honour unto <character
        who="Achilles">Achilles</character>; for I would fain keep in time to come thy worship and thy
    love. Haste thee with all speed to the host and declare unto thy son my bidding. Say unto him
    <action direction="at_someone" intention="negative" setting="public">that the gods are angered
        with him</action>, and that <emotion direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes" type="external"
            felt="wrath">I above all immortals am filled with wrath</emotion>, for that in the fury of his
    heart<lb/>he holdeth <character who="Hector">Hector</character> at the beaked ships and gave him
    not back, if so be he may be seized with fear of me and give <character who="Hector"
        >Hector</character> back. But I will send forth Iris unto <character who="Priam"
            epithet="positive">great-hearted Priam</character>, to bid him go to the ships of the Achaeans to
    ransom his dear son, and <action direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">to
        bear gifts</action> unto <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart."<lb/>
    <lb/>So spake he, and the goddess, silver-footed Thetis, failed not to hearken, <action
        direction="at_no-one" intention="positive" setting="public">but went darting down from the peaks
        of Olympus, and came to the hut of her son.</action> There she found him <action
            direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">groaning ceaselessly</action>, and
    round about him his dear comrades with busy haste were making ready their early meal,<lb/>and in
    the hut a ram, great and shaggy, lay slaughtered for them. Then she,<action direction="at_someone"
        intention="positive" setting="public">his queenly mother, sate her down close by his side and
        stroked him with her hand, and spake, and called him by name</action>:"My child, how long wilt
    thou devour thine heart with weeping and sorrowing, and wilt take no thought of food,<lb/>neither
    of the couch? Good were it for thee even to have dalliance in a woman's embrace. For, I tell thee,
    thou shalt not thyself be long in life, but even now doth death stand hard by thee and mighty fate.
    But hearken thou forthwith unto me, for I am a messenger unto thee from Zeus. He declareth that
    that <emotion felt="anger" type="external" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone">the gods are
        angered with thee</emotion>,<lb/>and that <emotion direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes"
            type="external" felt="wrath">himself above all immortals is filled with wrath</emotion>, for that
    in the fury of thine heart thou holdest <character who="Hector">Hector</character> at the beaked
    ships, and gavest him not back. Nay come, give him up, and take ransom for the dead." Then in
    answer to her spake <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles, swift of
        foot</character>: "So let it be; whoso bringeth ransom, let him bear away the dead,<lb/>if verily
    with full purpose of heart the Olympian himself so biddeth." On this wise amid the gathering of the
    ships mother and son spake many winged words one to the other, but the son of Cronos sent forth
    Iris to sacred Ilios:"Up, go, swift Iris; leave thou the abode of Olympus<lb/>and bear tidings
    within Ilios unto <character epithet="positive" who="Priam">great-hearted Priam</character> that he
    go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom his dear son, and that <action direction="at_someone"
        intention="positive" setting="public">he bear gifts</action> unto <character who="Achilles"
            >Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart; alone let him go, neither let any man
    beside of the Trojans go with him. A herald may attend him, an elder man,<lb/>to guide the mules
    and the light-running waggon, and to carry back to the city the dead, even him that <character
        who="Achilles">Achilles</character> slew. Let not death be in his thoughts. neither any fear; such
    a guide will we give him, even Argeiphontes, who shall lead him, until in his leading he bring him
    nigh to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>.<lb/>And when he shall have led him into the
    hut, neither shall <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> himself slay him nor suffer any
    other to slay; for not without wisdom is he, neither without purpose, nor yet hardened in sin; nay,
    with all kindliness will he spare a suppliant man."<lb/> So spake he, and storm-footed Iris hasted
    to bear his message.<lb/>She came to the house of <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, and
    found therein <action direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">clamour and
        wailing</action>. His <action direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">sons
            sat about their father within the court sullying their garments with their tears, and in their
            midst was the old king close-wrapped in his mantle; and upon the old man's head and neck was filth
            in abundance</action>,<lb/>which he had gathered in his hands as he grovelled on the earth. And
    <action direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">his daughters and his sons'
        wives were wailing throughout the house</action>, bethinking them of the warriors many and valiant
    who were lying low, slain by the hands of the Argives. And the messenger of Zeus drew nigh to
    <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, and spake to him;<lb/>softly she uttered her voice, yet
    trembling gat hold of his himbs:"Be of good courage, O <character who="Priam" epithet="neutral"
        >Priam, son of Dardanus</character>, and fear thou not at all. Not to forbode any evil to thee am
    I come hither, but with good intent. I am a messenger to thee from <character who="Gods"
        >Zeus</character>, who far away though he be, hath exceeding care for thee and pity.<lb/>The
    Olympian biddeth thee ransom goodly <character who="Hector">Hector</character>, and <action
        direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">bear gifts to</action>
    <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart; alone do thou go,
    neither let any man beside of the Trojans go with thee. A herald may attend thee, an elder man, to
    guide the mules and the light-running waggon,<lb/>and to carry back to the city the dead, even him
    that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> slew. Let not death be in thy thoughts, neither
    any fear; such a guide shall go with thee, even Argeiphontes, who shall lead thee, until in his
    heading he bring thee nigh to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>. And when he shall
    have led thee into the hut,<lb/>neither shall <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
    himself slay thee nor suffer any other to slay; for not without wisdom is he, neither without
    purpose, nor yet hardened in sin; nay, with all kindliness will he spare a suppliant man." When she
    had thus spoken swift-footed Iris departed; but the king bade his sons<lb/>make ready the running
    mule waggon, and bind the wicker box thereon. And himself <action setting="private"
        intention="positive" direction="at_no-one">he went down to the vaulted treasure-chamber</action>,
    fragrant of cedar wood and high of roof, that held jewels full many: and he called to him Hecabe
    his wife, and spake:"Lady, from <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> hath an Olympian messenger
    come to me,<lb/>that I go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom my dear son, and that I bear gifts
    to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart. But come, tell
    me this, how seemeth it to thy mind? For as touching mine own self, wondrously doth the desire of
    my heart bid me go thither to the ships, into the wide camp of the Achaeans."<lb/>
    <lb/>So spake he, but <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="private">his
        wife uttered a shrill cry, and spake in answer</action>:"Ah, woe is me, whither now is gone the
    wisdom for the which of old thou wast famed among stranger folk and among them thou rulest? How art
    thou fain to go alone to the ships of the Achaeans to meet the eyes of the man who<lb/>hath slain
    thy sons, many and valiant? Of iron verily is thy heart. For if so be he get thee in his power and
    his eyes behold thee, so savage and faithless is the man, he will neither pity thee nor anywise
    have reverence. Nay, let us now make our lament afar from him we mourn, abiding here in the hall.
    On this wise for him did mighty Fate spin<lb/>with her thread at his birth, when myself did bear
    him, that he should glut swift-footed dogs far from his parents, in the abode of a violent man, in
    whose inmost heart I were fain to fix my teeth and feed thereon; then haply might deeds of requital
    be wrought for my son, seeing in no wise while playing the dastard was he slain of him,<lb/>but
    while standing forth in defence of the men and deep-bosomed women of Troy, with no thought of
    shelter or of flight." Then <action setting="private" intention="positive" direction="at_someone"
        >in answer spake unto her the old man</action>, <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">god-like
            Priam</character>:"Seek not to stay me that am fain to go, neither be thyself a bird of ill-boding
    in my halls; thou shalt not persuade me.<lb/>For if any other of the men that are upon the face of
    the earth had bidden me this, whether of seers that divine from sacrifice or of priests, a false
    thing might we deem it, and turn away therefrom the more; but now—for myself I heard the voice of
    the goddess and looked upon her face—I will go forth, neither shall her word be vain. And if it be
    my fate<lb/>to lie dead by the ships of the brazen-coated Achaeans, so would I have it; forthwith
    let <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
    <action direction="at_someone" intention="negative" setting="public">slay me, when once I have
        clasped in my arms my son, and have put from me the desire for wailing</action>."<lb/> He spake,
    and opened the goodly lids of chests, wherefrom he took twelve beauteous robes<lb/>and twelve
    cloaks of single fold, and as many coverlets, and as many white mantles, and therewithal as many
    tunics. And of gold he weighed out and bare forth talents, ten in all, and two gleaming tripods,
    and four cauldrons, and a cup exceeding fair, that the men of Thrace had given him<lb/><action
        setting="public" intention="negative" direction="at_someone">when he went thither on an embassage,
        a great treasure; not even this did the old man spare in his halls, for he was exceeding fain to
        ransom his dear son.</action> Then drave he all the Trojans from out the portico, and chid them
    with words of reviling:"Get ye hence, wretches, ye that work me shame!<lb/>Have ye not also
    lamentation at home, that ye come hither to vex me? Count ye it not enough that <character
        who="Gods" epithet="neutral">Zeus, son of Cronos</character>, hath brought this sorrow upon me,
    that I should lose my son the best of all? Nay, but yourselves too shall know it, for easier shall
    ye be, now he is dead, for the Achaeans to slay.<lb/>But for me, or ever mine eyes behold the city
    sacked and laid waste, may I go down into the house of <character who="Gods">Hades</character>." He
    spake, and plying his staff went among the men, and they went forth from before the old man in his
    haste. Then called he aloud to his sons, chiding Helenus and Paris and goodly Agathon<lb/>and
    Pammon and Antiphonus and Polites, good at the war-cry, and Deiphobus and Hippothous and lordly
    Dius. To these nine the old man called aloud, and gave command:"Haste ye, base children that are my
    shame; would that ye all together in <character who="Hector">Hector</character>'s stead had been
    slain at the swift ships!<lb/>Woe is me, that am all unblest, seeing that I begat sons the best in
    the broad land of Troy, yet of them I avow that not one is left, not godlike Nestor, not Troilus
    the warrior charioteer, not <character who="Hector">Hector</character> that was a god among men,
    neither seemed he as the son of a mortal man, but of a god:<lb/>all them hath Ares slain, yet these
    things of shame are all left me, false of tongue, nimble of foot, peerless at beating the floor in
    the dance, robbers of lambs and kids from your own folk. <action direction="at_someone"
        intention="positive" setting="public">Will ye not make me ready a waggon, and that with speed, and
        lay all these things therein, that we may get forward on our way?</action>"<lb/><lb></lb>And the old man, <character epithet="positive" who="Priam">godlike Priam</character>, answered him: "If thou art indeed a squire of <character epithet="neutral" who="Achilles">Achilles, Peleus' son</character>
    come now, tell me all the truth, whether <character who="Hector">my son</character> is even yet by the ships or whether by
    now <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> hath <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public">hewn him limb from limb and cast him before his dogs.</action>" <lb/>Then again the
    messenger Argeiphontes spake to him:"Old sire, <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">not yet have dogs and birds devoured him, but still
        he lieth there beside the ship of <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> amid the huts as he was at the first; and this is now
        the twelfth day that he lieth there, yet his flesh decayeth not at all,<lb/>neither do worms
        consume it, such as devour men that be slain in fight</action>. Truly <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone"><character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> draggeth him ruthlessly about
            the barrow of <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus his dear comrade</character></action>, so oft as <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">sacred Dawn</character> appeareth, howbeit he marreth him not; thou
    wouldst thyself marvel, wert thou to come and see<action direction="at_someone" setting="public" intention="positive" relationship="neutral"> how dewy-fresh he lieth, and is washen clean of
        blood,</action><lb/>neither hath anywhere pollution;<action relationship="neutral" intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"> and all the wounds are closed wherewith he was
            stricken, for many there were that drave the bronze into his flesh.</action> <action intention="positive" direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" setting="public">In such wise do the <character who="Hector">blessed
                gods</character> care for <character who="Hector">thy son</character>, a corpse though he be, seeing he was dear unto <character who="Gods">their</character> hearts.</action>" So spake he,
    and the <character who="Priam">old man</character> <emotion felt="relief" direction="at_no-one" relationship="neutral" appropriate="yes" type="external">waxed glad</emotion>, and answered, saying:<lb/>"My child, a good thing is it in sooth e'en
    to give to the immortals such gifts as be due; for never did my son—as sure as ever such a one
    there was—forget in our halls the gods that hold Olympus; wherefore they have remembered this for
    him, even though he be in the doom of death. But come, <action intention="positive" setting="public" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone">take thou from me this fair goblet</action>,<lb/>and
    guard me myself, and guide me with the speeding of the gods, until I be come unto the hut of the
    <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles son of Pe1eus</character>." And again the messenger, Argeiphontes, spake to him:"Thou dost make trial of me,
    old sire, that am younger than thou; but thou shalt not prevail upon me, seeing thou biddest me
    take gifts from thee while <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> knoweth naught thereof.<lb/><emotion felt="fear" type="external" appropriate="yes" relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone">Of him have I fear and awe at
        heart, that I should defraud him, lest haply some evil befall me hereafter.</emotion> Howbeit as thy guide
    would I go even unto glorious Argos, attending thee with kindly care in a swift ship or on foot;
    nor would any man make light of thy guide and set upon thee."<lb/>
    <lb/>So spake the Helper, and leaping upon the chariot behind the horses quickly grasped in his
    hands the lash and reins, and breathed great might into the horses and mules. But when they were
    come to the walls and the trench that guarded the ships, even as the watchers were but now busying
    them about their supper,<lb/>upon all of these the messenger Argeiphontes shed sleep, <action intention="positive" direction="at_no-one" relationship="neutral" setting="public">and forthwith
        opened the gates, and thrust back the bars, and brought within Priam, and the splendid gifts upon
        the wain</action>. But when they were come to the hut of <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles Peleus' son</character>, the lofty hut which the Myrmidons had
    builded for their king,<lb/>hewing therefor beams of fir —and they had roofed it over with downy
    thatch, gathered from the meadows; and round it they reared for him, their king, a great court with
    thick-set pales; and the door thereof was held by one single bar of fir that<lb/>three Achaeans
    were wont to drive home, and three to draw back the great bolt of the door （three of the rest, but
    <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> would drive it home even of himself）—then verily the helper <character who="Gods">Hermes</character> opened the door for the
    old man, and brought in the glorious gifts for the <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles swift-footed son of Peleus</character>; and from the chariot
    he stepped down to the ground and spake, saying: <lb/>"Old sire, I that am come to thee am immortal
    god, even <character who="Gods">Hermes</character>; for <character who="Gods">the Father</character> sent me to guide thee on thy way. But now verily will I go back,
    neither come within <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' sight; good cause for wrath would it be that an immortal god should
    thus openly be entertained of mortals.<lb/>But go thou in,<action direction="at_someone" intention="positive" relationship="enemies" setting="private"> and clasp the knees of the <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral"> Achilles, son of Peleus</character>
        and entreat him by his father and his fair-haired mother and his child, that thou mayest stir his
        soul."</action><lb/> So spake <character who="Gods">Hermes</character>, and departed unto high Olympus; and <character who="Priam">Priam</character> leapt from his chariot to
    the ground,<lb/>and left there Idaeus, who abode holding the horses and mules; <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies">but <character who="Priam">the old man</character> went
        straight toward the house where <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles, dear to Zeus</character>, was wont to sit.</action> Therein he found <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>>,
    but his comrades sat apart: two only, the warrior Automedon and Alcimus, scion of <character who="Gods">Ares</character>,<lb/>waited
    busily upon him; <action relationship="romantic" direction="at_no-one" setting="private" intention="negative">and he was newly ceased from meat, even from eating and drinking, and the table
        yet stood by his side</action>. <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies"><emotion appropriate="yes" felt="fear" type="external" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies"
            >Unseen of these <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">great Priam </character>entered in, and coming close to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>,
            clasped in his hands his knees, and kissed his hands, the terrible, man-slaying hands that had
            slain his many sons.</emotion></action><lb/>And as when sore blindness of heart cometh upon a man, that in his own
    country slayeth another and escapeth to a land of strangers, to the house of some man of substance,
    <action relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone" setting="private" intention="positive"> and wonder holdeth them that look upon him; <emotion type="internal" felt="wonder" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" appropriate="yes" >even so was <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> seized with wonder</emotion> at sight of
        <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">godlike Priam</character>, and <emotion felt="wonder" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" type="internal" appropriate="yes">seized with wonder were the others likewise</emotion>, and they glanced one at the
        other.<lb/>But Priam made entreaty, and spake to him, saying: "Remember thy father, O <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles like
            to the gods</character>, whose years are even as mine, on the grievous threshold of old age. Him full likely
        the dwellers that be round about are entreating evilly, neither is there any to ward from him ruin
        and bane.<lb/>Howbeit, while he heareth of thee as yet alive he hath joy at heart, and therewithal
        hopeth day by day that he shall see his dear son returning from Troy-land. But I—I am utterly
        unblest, seeing I begat sons the best in the broad land of Troy, yet of them I avow that not one is
        left.<lb/>Fifty I had, when the sons of the Achaeans came; nineteen were born to me of the
        self-same womb, and the others women of the palace bare. Of these, many as they were, furious <character who="Gods">Ares</character>
        hath loosed the knees, and he that alone was left me, that by himself guarded the city and the
        men,<lb/>him thou slewest but now as he fought for his country, even <character who="Hector">Hector.</character> </action>
    <action intention="positive" relationship="familial" direction="at_no-one" setting="private"> For his sake am I now
        come to the ships of the Achaeans to win him back from thee, and I bear with me ransom past
        counting. Nay, have thou awe of the gods, <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, and </action><action direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral" intention="positive" setting="private">take pity on me, remembering thine own
            father. Lo, I am more piteous far than he,<lb/>and have endured what no other mortal on the face of
            earth hath yet endured, to reach forth my hand to the face of him that hath slain my sons."</action><lb/> <action setting="private" intention="positive" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone">So
                spake he, and in <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>"> he roused desire<emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes"> to weep for his father</emotion>; and he took the <character who="Priam">old man</character> by the
                hand, and gently put him from him. So the twain bethought them of their dead, and wept; the one for
                <character who="Hector" epithet="neutral">man-slaying Hector</character> wept sore,<lb/>the while he grovelled at <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' feet, but <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> wept for
                <emotion appropriate="yes" type="internal" felt="lament" relationship="familial" direction="at_someone"> his own father</emotion>, and <emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic" felt="lament" type="internal" appropriate="yes">now again for <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character></emotion>; and the sound of their moaning went up through the
                house. But when goodly <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> had had his fill of lamenting, and the longing therefor had
                departed from his heart and limbs,<lb/>forthwith then he sprang from his seat, and raised the old
                man by his hand, pitying his hoary head and hoary beard; and he spake and addressed him with winged
                words:"</action> Ah, unhappy man, full many in good sooth are the evils thou hast endured in thy soul. <action relationship="neutral" direction="at_no-one" intention="positive" setting="private">How
                    hadst thou the heart to come alone to the ships of the Achaeans,<lb/>to meet the eyes of me that
                    have slain thy sons many and valiant? Of iron verily is thy heart. But come, sit thou upon a seat,
                    and our sorrows will we suffer to lie quiet in our hearts, despite our pain; for no profit cometh
                    of chill lament.</action><lb/><action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="private">For on this wise have the gods spun the thread for wretched mortals, that they
                        should live in pain; and themselves are sorrowless. For two urns are set upon the floor of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> of
                        gifts that he giveth, the one of ills, the other of blessings. To whomsoever <character who="Gods" epithet="neutral">Zeus, that hurleth the
                            thunderbolt,</character> giveth a mingled lot,<lb/>that man meeteth now with evil, now with good; but to
                        whomsoever he giveth but of the baneful, him he maketh to be reviled of man, and direful madness
                        driveth him over the face of the sacred earth, and he wandereth honoured neither of gods nor
                        mortals.</action> Even so unto Peleus did the gods give glorious gifts<lb/>from his birth; for he excelled
    all men in good estate and in wealth, and was king over the Myrmidons, and to him that was but a
    mortal the gods gave a goddess to be his wife.<lb/>Howbeit even upon him the gods brought evil, in
    that there nowise sprang up in his halls offspring of princely sons, but he begat one only son,
    doomed to an untimely fate. Neither may I tend him as he groweth old, seeing that far, far from
    mine own country I abide in the land of Troy, vexing thee and thy children. And of thee, old sire,
    <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone"> we hear that of old thou wast blest</action>; how of all that toward the sea Lesbos, the seat of Macar,
    encloseth,<lb/>and Phrygia in the upland, and the boundless Hellespont, over all these folk, men
    say, thou, old sire, wast preeminent by reason of thy wealth and thy sons. Howbeit from the time
    when the heavenly gods brought upon thee this bane, ever around thy city are battles and slayings
    of men. Bear thou up, neither wail ever ceaselessly in thy heart; <action intention="positive" relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" setting="private">for naught wilt thou avail by
        <emotion felt="lament" appropriate = "yes" direction="at_someone" type="internal">grieving for thy son,<lb/>neither wilt thou bring him back to life</emotion></action>; ere that shalt thou suffer some
    other ill."<lb/> <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone">And the old man, <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">godlike Priam</character>, answered him:</action> "Seat me not anywise upon a chair, O
    <character who="Achilles">Achilles thou fostered of Zeus</character>, so long as <character who="Hector">Hector</character> <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public" relationship="enemies">lieth uncared-for amid the huts</action>;<lb/><action intention="positive" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone" setting="private">nay, give him back
        with speed, that mine eyes may behold him; and do thou accept the ransom, the great ransom, that we
        bring. So mayest thou have joy thereof, and come to thy native land, seeing that from the first
        thou hast spared me.</action>" <action relationship="enemies" intention="negative" setting="private" direction="at_someone">Then with an angry glance from beneath his brows spake to him<character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> swift
            of foot:</action><lb/>"Provoke me no more, old sir; I am minded even of myself to give <character who="Hector">Hector</character> back to thee;
    >>>>>>> fe9cb1715465256b0366eb238d50024609697b43
    for from <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> there came to me a messenger, even <character who="Gods">the mother that bare me</character>, daughter of the <character who="Gods">old man
        of the sea</character>. And of thee, <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, do I know in my heart—it nowise escapeth me—that some god led thee
    to the swift ships of the Achaeans.<lb/>For no mortal man, were he never so young and strong, would
    dare to come amid the host; neither could he then escape the watch, nor easily thrust back the bar
    of our doors. Wherefore now stir my heart no more amid my sorrows, lest, old sire, I spare not even
    thee within the huts,<lb/>my suppliant though thou art, and so sin against the behest of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>." So
    spake he, <emotion relationship="enemies" direction="at_no-one" appropriate="yes" type="internal" felt="fear">and the old man was seized with fear, and hearkened to his word</emotion>. But like a lion the <character who="Achilles">son
        of Peleus</character> sprang forth from the houses—not alone, for with him went two squires as well, even the
    warrior Automedon and Alcimus,<lb/>they that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> honoured above all his comrades, after the
    dead <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character>. These then loosed from beneath the yoke the horses and mules, and led within the
    herald, the crier of the old king, <action direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" setting="private" intention="negative">and set him on a chair;</action> and from the wain of goodly felloes they
    took the countless ransom for Hector's head.<lb/>But they left there two robes and a fair-woven
    tunic, to the end that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character><action intention="positive" setting="private" relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone"> might enwrap the dead therein and so give him to be borne to his
        home</action>. Then <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> called forth the hand-maids and bade them wash and anoint him, bearing him to a
    place apart that <character who="Priam">Priam</character> might not have sight of his son, lest in grief of heart he should not
    restrain his wrath,<lb/>whenso he had sight of his son, and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' own spirit be stirred to
    anger, and he slay him, and so sin against the behest of Zeus. <action direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" setting="private" intention="positive">So when the handmaids had washed the
        body and anointed it with oil, and had cast about it a fair cloak and a tunic, then <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
        himself lifted it and set it upon a bier,<lb/>and his comrades with him lifted it upon the polished
        waggon. Then he uttered a groan, and called by name upon his dear comrade:"Be not thou wroth with
        me, <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character>, if thou hearest even in the house of Hades that I have given back goodly Hector to
        his dear father, seeing that not unseemly is the ransom he hath given me.<lb/>And unto thee shall I
        render even of this all that is thy due."</action><lb/> So spake <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">goodly Achilles</character>, and went back within the
    hut and on the richly-wrought chair wherefrom he had risen sate him down by the opposite wall, and
    he spake unto <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, saying:"Thy son, old sire, is given back according to thy wish,<lb/>and lieth
    upon a bier; and at break of day thou shalt thyself behold him, as thou bearest him hence; but for
    this present let us bethink us of supper. For even the fair-haired Niobe bethought her of meat,
    albeit twelve children perished in her halls, six daughters and six lusty sons.<lb/>The sons <character who="Gods">Apollo</character>
    slew with shafts from his silver bow, being wroth against Niobe, and the daughters the archer
    <character who="Gods">Artemis</character>, for that Niobe had matched her with fair-cheeked <character who="Gods">Leto</character>, saying that the goddess had borne
    but twain, while herself was mother to many; wherefore they, for all they were but twain, destroyed
    them all.<lb/>For nine days' space they lay in their blood, nor was there any to bury them, for the
    son of Cronos turned the folk to stones; howbeit on the tenth day the gods of heaven buried them;
    and Niobe bethought her of meat, for she was wearied with the shedding of tears. And now somewhere
    amid the rocks, on the lonely mountains,<lb/>on Sipylus, where, men say, are the couching-places of
    goddesses, even of the nymphs that range swiftly in the dance about Achelous, there, albeit a
    stone, she broodeth over her woes sent by the gods. <action intention="positive" setting="private" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone"><emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral" felt="lament" type="external" appropriate="yes" >But come, let us twain likewise, noble old
        sire, bethink us of meat; and thereafter shalt thou make lament over thy dear son,<lb/>when thou
        hast borne him into Ilios; mourned shall he be of thee many tears."</emotion></action> <action relationship="neutral" direction="at_no-one" setting="private" intention="positive">Therewith <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">swift Achilles</character> sprang
            up, and slew a white-fleeced sheep, and his comrades flayed it and made it ready well and duly, and
            sliced it cunningly and spitted the morsels, and roasted them carefully and drew all off the
            spits.<lb/>And Automedon took bread and dealt it forth on the table in fair baskets, while <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
            dealt the meat. So they put forth their hands to the good cheer lying ready before them.</action> But when
    they had put from them the desire of food and drink, then verily <character who="Priam">Priam, son of Dardanus</character>, marvelled
    at <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, how tall he was and how comely;<lb/>for he was like the gods to look upon. And a son
    of Dardanus, did <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> marvel, beholding his goodly aspect and hearkening to his words. But when
    they had had their fill of gazing one upon the other, then the old man, <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">godlike Priam</character>, was first to
    speak, saying:<lb/>"Show me now my bed with speed, O <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">thou nurtured of Zeus</character>, that lulled at length
    by sweet sleep we may rest and take our joy; for never yet have mine eyes closed beneath mine
    eyelids since at thy hands my son lost his life, but ever do I wail and brood over my countless
    sorrows,<lb/>grovelling in the filth in the closed spaces of the court. But now have I tasted of
    meat, and have let flaming wine pass down my throat; whereas till now had I tasted naught."<lb/> He
    spake, and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">bade his comrades and the handmaids set bedsteads beneath the portico,<lb/>and
        to lay on them fair purple blankets, and to spread thereover coverlets, and on these to put fleecy
        cloaks for clothing. So the maids went forth from the hall with torches in their hands, and
        straightway spread two beds in busy haste</action>. Then mockingly spake unto <character who="Priam">Priam</character> <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles, swift of
            foot</character>:<lb/>"Without do thou lay thee down, dear old sire, lest there come hither one of the
    counsellors of the Achaeans, that ever sit by my side and take counsel, as is meet. If one of these
    were to have sight of thee through the swift black night, forthwith might he haply tell it to
    <character who="Agamemnon" epithet="neutral">Agamemnon, shepherd of the host</character>,<lb/>and so should there arise delay in the giving back of the
    body. But come, tell me this, and declare it truly: for how many days' space thou art minded to
    make funeral for <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">goodly Hector</character>, to the end that for so long I may myself abide, and may keep back
    the host." And the old man,<character who="Priam" epithet="positive"> godlike Priam</character>, answered him: saying:<lb/>"If thou indeed art willing
    that I accomplish for goodly Hector his burial, then in doing on this wise, O <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, wilt thou
    do according to my wish. Thou knowest how we are pent within the city, and far is it to fetch wood
    from the mountain, and the Trojans are sore afraid.<lb/><action relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" setting="public" intention="positive">For nine days' space will we wail for him
        in our halls, and on the tenth will we make his funeral, and the folk shall feast, and on the
        eleventh will we heap a barrow over him, and on the twelfth will we do battle, if so be we must.</action>"
    Then spake to him in answer <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly Achilles</character>:"Thus shall this also be aged Priam, even
    as thou wouldest have it;<lb/>for <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">I will hold back the battle for such time as thou dost bid.</action>" When
    he had thus spoken he clasped the old man's right hand by the wrist, lest his heart should any wise
    wax fearful. So they laid them to sleep there in the fore-hall of the house, the herald and <character who="Priam">Priam</character>,
    with hearts of wisdom in their breasts;<lb/>but <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> slept in the innermost part of the
    well-builded hut, and by his side lay fair-cheeked Briseis.<lb/> Now all the other gods and men,
    lords of chariots, slumbered the whole night through, overcome of soft sleep; but not upon the
    <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">helper Hermes</character> might sleep lay hold,<lb/>as he pondered in mind how he should guide king <character who="Priam">Priam</character> forth
    from the ships unmarked of the strong keepers of the gate. He took his stand above his head and
    spake to him, saying:"Old sire, no thought then hast thou of any evil, that thou still sleepest
    thus amid foemen, for that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> has spared thee.<lb/>Now verily hast thou ransomed thy son, and
    a great price thou gavest. But for thine own life must the sons thou hast, they that be left
    behind, give ransorn thrice so great, if so be Agamemnon, Atreus' son, have knowledge of thee, or
    the host of the Achaeans have knowledge." So spake he, and <emotion relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes" type="internal" felt="fear">the old man was seized with fear</emotion>, and
    made the herald to arise.<lb/><action direction="at_no-one" relationship="neutral" setting="public" intention="positive">And <character who="Gods">Hermes</character> yoked for them the horses and mules, and himself lightly
        drave them through the camp, neither had any man knowledge thereof.</action> But when they were now come to
    the ford of the fair-flowing river, even eddying Xanthus, that immortal <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> begat, then <character who="Gods">Hermes</character>
    departed to high Olympus,<lb/>and <character who="Gods">Dawn</character>, the saffron-robed, was spreading over the face of all the
    earth. <action intention="positive" setting="public" relationship="familial" direction="at_no-one">So they with moaning and wailing drave the horses to the city, and the mules bare the dead.</action>
    Neither was any other ware of them, whether man or fair-girdled woman; but in truth Cassandra, peer
    of golden Aphrodite,<lb/>having gone up upon Pergamus, marked her dear father as he stood in the
    car, and the herald, the city's crier; and she had sight of that other lying on the bier in the
    waggon drawn of the mules. Thereat she uttered a shrill cry, and called throughout all the
    town:"Come ye, men and women of Troy, and behold Hector,<lb/>if ever while yet he lived ye had joy
    of his coming back from battle; since great joy was he to the city and to all the folk."<lb/> So
    spake she, nor was any man left there within the city, neither any woman, for upon all had come
    grief that might not be borne; and hard by the gates they met <character who="Priam" epithet="neutral">Priam</character>, as he bare home the
    dead.<lb/><action direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" setting="public" intention="positive"><emotion relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" felt="lament" type="external" appropriate="yes">First Hector's dear wife and queenly mother flung themselves upon the light-running
        waggon, and clasping his head the while, wailed and tore their hair; and the folk thronged about
        and wept. And now the whole day long until set of sun had they made lament for Hector with shedding
        of tears there without the gates,<lb/>had not the old man spoken amid the folk from out the
        car:"<action direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" intention="positive" setting="public">Make me way for the mules to pass through; thereafter shall ye take your fill of wailing, when
            I have brought him to the house." So spake he, and they stood apart and made way for the waggon.
            But the others, when they had brought him to the glorious house,<lb/>laid him on a corded bedstead,
            and by his side set singers, leaders of the dirge, who led the song of lamentation—they chanted the
            dirge, and thereat the women made lament. And amid these white-armed <emotion relationship="romantic" direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes" type="external" felt="lament">Andromache led the wailing,</emotion>
            holding in her arms the while the head of <character who="Hector" epithet="negative">man-slaying Hector</character>:<lb/>"Husband, perished from out of
            life art thou, <emotion felt="lament" type="external" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">yet in thy youth, and leavest me a widow in thy halls; and thy son is still but a
                babe, the son born of thee and me in our haplessness; neither do I deem that he will come to
                manhood, for ere that shall this city be wasted utterly.</emotion></action>. For thou hast perished that didst watch
        thereover,<lb/>thou that didst guard it, and keep safe its noble wives and little children. These,
        I ween, shall soon be riding upon the hollow ships, and I among them; and thou, my child, shalt
        follow with me to a place where thou shalt labour at unseemly tasks, toiling before the face of
        some ungentle master, or else some Achaean shall seize thee by the arm<lb/>and hurl thee from the
        wall, a woeful death,</emotion> being wroth for that <character who="Hector" >Hector</character> slew his brother haply, or his father, or his
        son, seeing that full many Achaeans at the hands of <character who="Hector">Hector</character> have bitten the vast earth with their
        teeth; for nowise gentle was thy father in woeful war.<lb/>Therefore the folk wail for him
        throughout the city, and grief unspeakable and sorrow hast thou brought upon thy parents, <character who="Hector">Hector</character>;
        and for me beyond all others shall grievous woes be left. For at thy death thou didst neither
        stretch out thy hands to me from thy bed, nor speak to me any word of wisdom whereon<lb/>I might
        have pondered night and day with shedding of tears."<lb/> So spake she wailing, and thereat the
        women made lament. And among them Hecabe in turns led the vehement wailing:"<character who="Hector">Hector</character>, far dearest to
        my heart of all my children, lo, when thou livedst thou wast dear to the gods,<lb/>and therefore
        have they had care of thee for all thou art in the doom of death. For of other sons of mine
        whomsoever he took would swift-footed <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> sell beyond the unresting sea, unto Samos and Imbros
        and Lemnos, shrouded in smoke, but, when from thee he had taken away thy life with the long-edged
        bronze<lb/>oft would he drag thee about the barrow of his comrade, <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character>, whom thou didst slay;
        howbeit even so might he not raise him up. all dewy-fresh thou liest in my halls as wert thou g
        newly slain, like as one whom Apollo of the silver bow assaileth with his gentle shafts and
        slayeth." <lb/><action relationship="romantic" direction="at_someone" setting="public" intention="positive">So spake she wailing, and roused unabating lament</action>. <emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" appropriate="yes" type="external" felt="lament">And thereafter Helen was the
            third to lead the wailing:</emotion>"<character who="Hector">Hector</character>, far dearest to my heart of all my husband's brethren! In sooth
        my husband is godlike Alexander, that brought me to Troy-land —would I died ere then!<lb/>For this
        is now the twentieth year from the time when I went from thence and am gone from my native land,
        but never yet heard I evil or despiteful word from thee; nay, if so be any other spake
        reproachfully of me in the halls, a brother of thine or a sister, or brother's fair-robed
        wife,<lb/>or thy mother—but thy father was ever gentle as he had been mine own—yet wouldst thou
        turn them with speech and restrain them by the gentleness of thy spirit and thy gentle words.
        Wherefore I wail alike for thee and for my hapless self with grief at heart; for no longer have I
        anyone beside in broad Troy<lb/>that is gentle to me or kind; but all men shudder at me."<lb/> So
        spake she wailing, and thereat the countless throng made moan. But the old man <character who="Priam">Priam</character> spake among
        the folk, saying:<action relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">"Bring wood now, ye men of Troy, unto the city, neither have ye anywise fear at
            heart of a cunning ambush of the Argives</action>; for verily <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> laid upon me this word<lb/>when he
        sent me forth from the black ships, that he would do us no hurt until the twelfth dawn be come." So
        spake he, and they yoked oxen and mules to waggons, and speedily thereafter gathered together
        before the city. For nine days' space they brought in measureless store of wood,<lb/>but when the
        tenth Dawn arose, giving light unto mortals, then bare they forth <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">bold Hector</character>, shedding tears the
        while, and on the topmost pyre they laid the dead man, and cast fire thereon.</action> <action setting="public" intention="positive" direction="at_someone" relationship="familial">But soon as early
            <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">Dawn appeared, the rosy-fingered</character>, then gathered the folk about the pyre of <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">glorious Hector</character>.<lb/>And
            when they were assembled and met together, first they quenched with flaming wine all the pyre, so
            far as the fire's might had come upon it, and thereafter his brethren and his comrades gathered the
            white bones, mourning, and big tears flowed ever down their cheeks.<lb/>The bones they took and
            placed in a golden urn, covering them over with soft purple robes, and quickly laid the urn in a
            hollow grave, and covered it over with great close-set stones. </action><action intention="positive" direction="at_no-one" setting="public" relationship="familial">Then with spe'[ed heaped they the
                mound, and round about were watchers set on every side,<lb/>lest the well-greaved Achaeans should
                set upon them before the time. And when they had piled the barrow they went back, and gathering
                together duly feasted a glorious feast in the palace </action> of <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">Priam, the king fostered of </character><character who="Gods">Zeus</character><action intention="positive" relationship="familial" setting="public" direction="at_someone"> On this
                    wise held they funeral for <character who="Hector" epithet="neutral">horse-taming Hector</character>.</action>

</book>
