<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="UPDATEDSCHEMA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<book>
 <lb></lb>And the old man, <character epithet="positive" who="Priam">godlike Priam</character>, answered him: "If thou art indeed a squire of <character epithet="neutral" who="Achilles">Achilles, Peleus' son</character>
 come now, tell me all the truth, whether <character who="Hector">my son</character> is even yet by the ships or whether by
 now <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> hath <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public">hewn him limb from limb and cast him before his dogs.</action>" <lb/>Then again the
 messenger Argeiphontes spake to him:"Old sire, <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">not yet have dogs and birds devoured him, but still
 he lieth there beside the ship of <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> amid the huts as he was at the first; and this is now
 the twelfth day that he lieth there, yet his flesh decayeth not at all,<lb/>neither do worms
 consume it, such as devour men that be slain in fight</action>. Truly <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone"><character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> draggeth him ruthlessly about
 the barrow of <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus his dear comrade</character></action>, so oft as <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">sacred Dawn</character> appeareth, howbeit he marreth him not; thou
 wouldst thyself marvel, wert thou to come and see<action direction="at_someone" setting="public" intention="positive" relationship="neutral"> how dewy-fresh he lieth, and is washen clean of
 blood,</action><lb/>neither hath anywhere pollution;<action relationship="neutral" intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"> and all the wounds are closed wherewith he was
 stricken, for many there were that drave the bronze into his flesh.</action> <action intention="positive" direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" setting="public">In such wise do the <character who="Hector">blessed
 gods</character> care for <character who="Hector">thy son</character>, a corpse though he be, seeing he was dear unto <character who="Gods">their</character> hearts.</action>" So spake he,
 and the <character who="Priam">old man</character> <emotion felt="relief" direction="at_no-one" relationship="neutral" appropriate="yes" type="external">waxed glad</emotion>, and answered, saying:<lb/>"My child, a good thing is it in sooth e'en
 to give to the immortals such gifts as be due; for never did my son—as sure as ever such a one
 there was—forget in our halls the gods that hold Olympus; wherefore they have remembered this for
 him, even though he be in the doom of death. But come, <action intention="positive" setting="public" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone">take thou from me this fair goblet</action>,<lb/>and
 guard me myself, and guide me with the speeding of the gods, until I be come unto the hut of the
 <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles son of Pe1eus</character>." And again the messenger, Argeiphontes, spake to him:"Thou dost make trial of me,
 old sire, that am younger than thou; but thou shalt not prevail upon me, seeing thou biddest me
 take gifts from thee while <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> knoweth naught thereof.<lb/><emotion felt="fear" type="external" appropriate="yes" relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone">Of him have I fear and awe at
 heart, that I should defraud him, lest haply some evil befall me hereafter.</emotion> Howbeit as thy guide
 would I go even unto glorious Argos, attending thee with kindly care in a swift ship or on foot;
 nor would any man make light of thy guide and set upon thee."<lb/>
 <lb/>So spake the Helper, and leaping upon the chariot behind the horses quickly grasped in his
 hands the lash and reins, and breathed great might into the horses and mules. But when they were
 come to the walls and the trench that guarded the ships, even as the watchers were but now busying
 them about their supper,<lb/>upon all of these the messenger Argeiphontes shed sleep, <action intention="positive" direction="at_no-one" relationship="neutral" setting="public">and forthwith
 opened the gates, and thrust back the bars, and brought within Priam, and the splendid gifts upon
 the wain</action>. But when they were come to the hut of <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles Peleus' son</character>, the lofty hut which the Myrmidons had
 builded for their king,<lb/>hewing therefor beams of fir —and they had roofed it over with downy
 thatch, gathered from the meadows; and round it they reared for him, their king, a great court with
 thick-set pales; and the door thereof was held by one single bar of fir that<lb/>three Achaeans
 were wont to drive home, and three to draw back the great bolt of the door （three of the rest, but
 <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> would drive it home even of himself）—then verily the helper <character who="Gods">Hermes</character> opened the door for the
 old man, and brought in the glorious gifts for the <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles swift-footed son of Peleus</character>; and from the chariot
 he stepped down to the ground and spake, saying: <lb/>"Old sire, I that am come to thee am immortal
 god, even <character who="Gods">Hermes</character>; for <character who="Gods">the Father</character> sent me to guide thee on thy way. But now verily will I go back,
 neither come within <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' sight; good cause for wrath would it be that an immortal god should
 thus openly be entertained of mortals.<lb/>But go thou in,<action direction="at_someone" intention="positive" relationship="enemies" setting="private"> and clasp the knees of the <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral"> Achilles, son of Peleus</character>
 and entreat him by his father and his fair-haired mother and his child, that thou mayest stir his
 soul."</action><lb/> So spake <character who="Gods">Hermes</character>, and departed unto high Olympus; and <character who="Priam">Priam</character> leapt from his chariot to
 the ground,<lb/>and left there Idaeus, who abode holding the horses and mules; <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies">but <character who="Priam">the old man</character> went
 straight toward the house where <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles, dear to Zeus</character>, was wont to sit.</action> Therein he found <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>>,
 but his comrades sat apart: two only, the warrior Automedon and Alcimus, scion of <character who="Gods">Ares</character>,<lb/>waited
 busily upon him; <action relationship="romantic" direction="at_no-one" setting="private" intention="negative">and he was newly ceased from meat, even from eating and drinking, and the table
 yet stood by his side</action>. <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies"><emotion appropriate="yes" felt="fear" type="external" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies"
>Unseen of these <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">great Priam </character>entered in, and coming close to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>,
 clasped in his hands his knees, and kissed his hands, the terrible, man-slaying hands that had
 slain his many sons.</emotion></action><lb/>And as when sore blindness of heart cometh upon a man, that in his own
 country slayeth another and escapeth to a land of strangers, to the house of some man of substance,
<action relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone" setting="private" intention="positive"> and wonder holdeth them that look upon him; <emotion type="internal" felt="wonder" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" appropriate="yes" >even so was <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> seized with wonder</emotion> at sight of
 <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">godlike Priam</character>, and <emotion felt="wonder" direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" type="internal" appropriate="yes">seized with wonder were the others likewise</emotion>, and they glanced one at the
 other.<lb/>But Priam made entreaty, and spake to him, saying: "Remember thy father, O <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles like
 to the gods</character>, whose years are even as mine, on the grievous threshold of old age. Him full likely
 the dwellers that be round about are entreating evilly, neither is there any to ward from him ruin
 and bane.<lb/>Howbeit, while he heareth of thee as yet alive he hath joy at heart, and therewithal
 hopeth day by day that he shall see his dear son returning from Troy-land. But I—I am utterly
 unblest, seeing I begat sons the best in the broad land of Troy, yet of them I avow that not one is
 left.<lb/>Fifty I had, when the sons of the Achaeans came; nineteen were born to me of the
 self-same womb, and the others women of the palace bare. Of these, many as they were, furious <character who="Gods">Ares</character>
 hath loosed the knees, and he that alone was left me, that by himself guarded the city and the
 men,<lb/>him thou slewest but now as he fought for his country, even <character who="Hector">Hector.</character> 
 <action intention="positive" relationship="familial" direction="at_no-one" setting="private"> For his sake am I now
 come to the ships of the Achaeans to win him back from thee,</action> and I bear with me ransom past
 counting. Nay, have thou awe of the gods, <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, and <action direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral" intention="positive" setting="private">take pity on me, remembering thine own
 father</action>. Lo, I am more piteous far than he,<lb/>and have endured what no other mortal on the face of
 earth hath yet endured, to reach forth my hand to the face of him that hath slain my sons."</action><lb/> <action setting="private" intention="positive" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone">So
 spake he, and in <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>"> he roused desire<emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes"> to weep for his father</emotion>; and he took the <character who="Priam">old man</character> by the
 hand, and gently put him from him. So the twain bethought them of their dead, and wept; the one for
 <character who="Hector" epithet="neutral">man-slaying Hector</character> wept sore,<lb/>the while he grovelled at <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' feet, but <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> wept for
<emotion appropriate="yes" type="internal" felt="lament" relationship="familial" direction="at_someone"> his own father</emotion>, and <emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic" felt="lament" type="internal" appropriate="yes">now again for <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character></emotion>; and the sound of their moaning went up through the
 house. But when goodly <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> had had his fill of lamenting, and the longing therefor had
 departed from his heart and limbs,<lb/>forthwith then he sprang from his seat, and raised the old
 man by his hand, pitying his hoary head and hoary beard; and he spake and addressed him with winged
 words:"</action> Ah, unhappy man, full many in good sooth are the evils thou hast endured in thy soul. <action relationship="neutral" direction="at_no-one" intention="positive" setting="private">How
 hadst thou the heart to come alone to the ships of the Achaeans,<lb/>to meet the eyes of me that
 have slain thy sons many and valiant? Of iron verily is thy heart. But come, sit thou upon a seat,
 and our sorrows will we suffer to lie quiet in our hearts, despite our pain; for no profit cometh
 of chill lament.</action><lb/><action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="private">For on this wise have the gods spun the thread for wretched mortals, that they
 should live in pain; and themselves are sorrowless. For two urns are set upon the floor of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> of
 gifts that he giveth, the one of ills, the other of blessings. To whomsoever <character who="Gods" epithet="neutral">Zeus, that hurleth the
 thunderbolt,</character> giveth a mingled lot,<lb/>that man meeteth now with evil, now with good; but to
 whomsoever he giveth but of the baneful, him he maketh to be reviled of man, and direful madness
 driveth him over the face of the sacred earth, and he wandereth honoured neither of gods nor
 mortals.</action> Even so unto Peleus did the gods give glorious gifts<lb/>from his birth; for he excelled
 all men in good estate and in wealth, and was king over the Myrmidons, and to him that was but a
 mortal the gods gave a goddess to be his wife.<lb/>Howbeit even upon him the gods brought evil, in
 that there nowise sprang up in his halls offspring of princely sons, but he begat one only son,
 doomed to an untimely fate. Neither may I tend him as he groweth old, seeing that far, far from
 mine own country I abide in the land of Troy, vexing thee and thy children. And of thee, old sire,
<action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone"> we hear that of old thou wast blest</action>; how of all that toward the sea Lesbos, the seat of Macar,
 encloseth,<lb/>and Phrygia in the upland, and the boundless Hellespont, over all these folk, men
 say, thou, old sire, wast preeminent by reason of thy wealth and thy sons. Howbeit from the time
 when the heavenly gods brought upon thee this bane, ever around thy city are battles and slayings
 of men. Bear thou up, neither wail ever ceaselessly in thy heart; <action intention="positive" relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" setting="private">for naught wilt thou avail by
 <emotion felt="lament" appropriate = "yes" direction="at_someone" type="internal">grieving for thy son,<lb/>neither wilt thou bring him back to life</emotion></action>; ere that shalt thou suffer some
 other ill."<lb/> <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone">And the old man, <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">godlike Priam</character>, answered him:</action> "Seat me not anywise upon a chair, O
<character who="Achilles">Achilles thou fostered of Zeus</character>, so long as <character who="Hector">Hector</character> <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public" relationship="enemies">lieth uncared-for amid the huts</action>;<lb/><action intention="positive" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone" setting="private">nay, give him back
 with speed, that mine eyes may behold him; and do thou accept the ransom, the great ransom, that we
 bring. So mayest thou have joy thereof, and come to thy native land, seeing that from the first
 thou hast spared me.</action>" <action relationship="enemies" intention="negative" setting="private" direction="at_someone">Then with an angry glance from beneath his brows spake to him<character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> swift
 of foot:</action><lb/>"Provoke me no more, old sir; I am minded even of myself to give <character who="Hector">Hector</character> back to thee;
>>>>>>> fe9cb1715465256b0366eb238d50024609697b43
 for from <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> there came to me a messenger, even <character who="Gods">the mother that bare me</character>, daughter of the <character who="Gods">old man
 of the sea</character>. And of thee, <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, do I know in my heart—it nowise escapeth me—that some god led thee
 to the swift ships of the Achaeans.<lb/>For no mortal man, were he never so young and strong, would
 dare to come amid the host; neither could he then escape the watch, nor easily thrust back the bar
 of our doors. Wherefore now stir my heart no more amid my sorrows, lest, old sire, I spare not even
 thee within the huts,<lb/>my suppliant though thou art, and so sin against the behest of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>." So
 spake he, <emotion relationship="enemies" direction="at_no-one" appropriate="yes" type="internal" felt="fear">and the old man was seized with fear, and hearkened to his word</emotion>. But like a lion the <character who="Achilles">son
 of Peleus</character> sprang forth from the houses—not alone, for with him went two squires as well, even the
 warrior Automedon and Alcimus,<lb/>they that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> honoured above all his comrades, after the
 dead <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character>. These then loosed from beneath the yoke the horses and mules, and led within the
 herald, the crier of the old king, <action direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" setting="private" intention="negative">and set him on a chair;</action> and from the wain of goodly felloes they
 took the countless ransom for Hector's head.<lb/>But they left there two robes and a fair-woven
 tunic, to the end that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character><action intention="positive" setting="private" relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone"> might enwrap the dead therein and so give him to be borne to his
 home</action>. Then <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> called forth the hand-maids and bade them wash and anoint him, bearing him to a
 place apart that <character who="Priam">Priam</character> might not have sight of his son, lest in grief of heart he should not
 restrain his wrath,<lb/>whenso he had sight of his son, and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>' own spirit be stirred to
 anger, and he slay him, and so sin against the behest of Zeus. <action direction="at_someone" relationship="enemies" setting="private" intention="positive">So when the handmaids had washed the
 body and anointed it with oil, and had cast about it a fair cloak and a tunic, then <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
 himself lifted it and set it upon a bier,<lb/>and his comrades with him lifted it upon the polished
 waggon. Then he uttered a groan, and called by name upon his dear comrade:"Be not thou wroth with
 me, <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character>, if thou hearest even in the house of Hades that I have given back goodly Hector to
 his dear father, seeing that not unseemly is the ransom he hath given me.<lb/>And unto thee shall I
 render even of this all that is thy due."</action><lb/> So spake <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">goodly Achilles</character>, and went back within the
 hut and on the richly-wrought chair wherefrom he had risen sate him down by the opposite wall, and
 he spake unto <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, saying:"Thy son, old sire, is given back according to thy wish,<lb/>and lieth
 upon a bier; and at break of day thou shalt thyself behold him, as thou bearest him hence; but for
 this present let us bethink us of supper. For even the fair-haired Niobe bethought her of meat,
 albeit twelve children perished in her halls, six daughters and six lusty sons.<lb/>The sons <character who="Gods">Apollo</character>
 slew with shafts from his silver bow, being wroth against Niobe, and the daughters the archer
 <character who="Gods">Artemis</character>, for that Niobe had matched her with fair-cheeked <character who="Gods">Leto</character>, saying that the goddess had borne
 but twain, while herself was mother to many; wherefore they, for all they were but twain, destroyed
 them all.<lb/>For nine days' space they lay in their blood, nor was there any to bury them, for the
 son of Cronos turned the folk to stones; howbeit on the tenth day the gods of heaven buried them;
 and Niobe bethought her of meat, for she was wearied with the shedding of tears. And now somewhere
 amid the rocks, on the lonely mountains,<lb/>on Sipylus, where, men say, are the couching-places of
 goddesses, even of the nymphs that range swiftly in the dance about Achelous, there, albeit a
 stone, she broodeth over her woes sent by the gods. <action intention="positive" setting="private" relationship="neutral" direction="at_someone"><emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral" felt="lament" type="external" appropriate="yes" >But come, let us twain likewise, noble old
 sire, bethink us of meat; and thereafter shalt thou make lament over thy dear son,<lb/>when thou
 hast borne him into Ilios; mourned shall he be of thee many tears."</emotion></action> <action relationship="neutral" direction="at_no-one" setting="private" intention="positive">Therewith <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">swift Achilles</character> sprang
 up, and slew a white-fleeced sheep, and his comrades flayed it and made it ready well and duly, and
 sliced it cunningly and spitted the morsels, and roasted them carefully and drew all off the
 spits.<lb/>And Automedon took bread and dealt it forth on the table in fair baskets, while <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
 dealt the meat. So they put forth their hands to the good cheer lying ready before them.</action> But when
 they had put from them the desire of food and drink, then verily <character who="Priam">Priam, son of Dardanus</character>, marvelled
 at <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, how tall he was and how comely;<lb/>for he was like the gods to look upon. And a son
 of Dardanus, did <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> marvel, beholding his goodly aspect and hearkening to his words. But when
 they had had their fill of gazing one upon the other, then the old man, <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">godlike Priam</character>, was first to
 speak, saying:<lb/>"Show me now my bed with speed, O <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">thou nurtured of Zeus</character>, that lulled at length
 by sweet sleep we may rest and take our joy; for never yet have mine eyes closed beneath mine
 eyelids since at thy hands my son lost his life, but ever do I wail and brood over my countless
 sorrows,<lb/>grovelling in the filth in the closed spaces of the court. But now have I tasted of
 meat, and have let flaming wine pass down my throat; whereas till now had I tasted naught."<lb/> He
 spake, and <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> <action intention="positive" setting="private" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">bade his comrades and the handmaids set bedsteads beneath the portico,<lb/>and
 to lay on them fair purple blankets, and to spread thereover coverlets, and on these to put fleecy
 cloaks for clothing. So the maids went forth from the hall with torches in their hands, and
 straightway spread two beds in busy haste</action>. Then mockingly spake unto <character who="Priam">Priam</character> <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles, swift of
 foot</character>:<lb/>"Without do thou lay thee down, dear old sire, lest there come hither one of the
 counsellors of the Achaeans, that ever sit by my side and take counsel, as is meet. If one of these
 were to have sight of thee through the swift black night, forthwith might he haply tell it to
 <character who="Agamemnon" epithet="neutral">Agamemnon, shepherd of the host</character>,<lb/>and so should there arise delay in the giving back of the
 body. But come, tell me this, and declare it truly: for how many days' space thou art minded to
 make funeral for <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">goodly Hector</character>, to the end that for so long I may myself abide, and may keep back
 the host." And the old man,<character who="Priam" epithet="positive"> godlike Priam</character>, answered him: saying:<lb/>"If thou indeed art willing
 that I accomplish for goodly Hector his burial, then in doing on this wise, O <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, wilt thou
 do according to my wish. Thou knowest how we are pent within the city, and far is it to fetch wood
 from the mountain, and the Trojans are sore afraid.<lb/><action relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" setting="public" intention="positive">For nine days' space will we wail for him
 in our halls, and on the tenth will we make his funeral, and the folk shall feast, and on the
 eleventh will we heap a barrow over him, and on the twelfth will we do battle, if so be we must.</action>"
 Then spake to him in answer <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly Achilles</character>:"Thus shall this also be aged Priam, even
 as thou wouldest have it;<lb/>for <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">I will hold back the battle for such time as thou dost bid.</action>" When
 he had thus spoken he clasped the old man's right hand by the wrist, lest his heart should any wise
 wax fearful. So they laid them to sleep there in the fore-hall of the house, the herald and <character who="Priam">Priam</character>,
 with hearts of wisdom in their breasts;<lb/>but <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> slept in the innermost part of the
 well-builded hut, and by his side lay fair-cheeked Briseis.<lb/> Now all the other gods and men,
 lords of chariots, slumbered the whole night through, overcome of soft sleep; but not upon the
 <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">helper Hermes</character> might sleep lay hold,<lb/>as he pondered in mind how he should guide king <character who="Priam">Priam</character> forth
 from the ships unmarked of the strong keepers of the gate. He took his stand above his head and
 spake to him, saying:"Old sire, no thought then hast thou of any evil, that thou still sleepest
 thus amid foemen, for that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> has spared thee.<lb/>Now verily hast thou ransomed thy son, and
 a great price thou gavest. But for thine own life must the sons thou hast, they that be left
 behind, give ransorn thrice so great, if so be Agamemnon, Atreus' son, have knowledge of thee, or
 the host of the Achaeans have knowledge." So spake he, and <emotion relationship="enemies" direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes" type="internal" felt="fear">the old man was seized with fear</emotion>, and
 made the herald to arise.<lb/><action direction="at_no-one" relationship="neutral" setting="public" intention="positive">And <character who="Gods">Hermes</character> yoked for them the horses and mules, and himself lightly
 drave them through the camp, neither had any man knowledge thereof.</action> But when they were now come to
 the ford of the fair-flowing river, even eddying Xanthus, that immortal <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> begat, then <character who="Gods">Hermes</character>
 departed to high Olympus,<lb/>and <character who="Gods">Dawn</character>, the saffron-robed, was spreading over the face of all the
 earth. <action intention="positive" setting="public" relationship="familial" direction="at_no-one">So they with moaning and wailing drave the horses to the city, and the mules bare the dead.</action>
 Neither was any other ware of them, whether man or fair-girdled woman; but in truth Cassandra, peer
 of golden Aphrodite,<lb/>having gone up upon Pergamus, marked her dear father as he stood in the
 car, and the herald, the city's crier; and she had sight of that other lying on the bier in the
 waggon drawn of the mules. Thereat she uttered a shrill cry, and called throughout all the
 town:"Come ye, men and women of Troy, and behold Hector,<lb/>if ever while yet he lived ye had joy
 of his coming back from battle; since great joy was he to the city and to all the folk."<lb/> So
 spake she, nor was any man left there within the city, neither any woman, for upon all had come
 grief that might not be borne; and hard by the gates they met <character who="Priam" epithet="neutral">Priam</character>, as he bare home the
 dead.<lb/><action direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" setting="public" intention="positive"><emotion relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" felt="lament" type="external" appropriate="yes">First Hector's dear wife and queenly mother flung themselves upon the light-running
 waggon, and clasping his head the while, wailed and tore their hair; and the folk thronged about
 and wept. And now the whole day long until set of sun had they made lament for Hector with shedding
 of tears there without the gates,<lb/>had not the old man spoken amid the folk from out the
 car:"<action direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" intention="positive" setting="public">Make me way for the mules to pass through; thereafter shall ye take your fill of wailing, when
 I have brought him to the house." So spake he, and they stood apart and made way for the waggon.
 But the others, when they had brought him to the glorious house,<lb/>laid him on a corded bedstead,
 and by his side set singers, leaders of the dirge, who led the song of lamentation—they chanted the
 dirge, and thereat the women made lament. And amid these white-armed <emotion relationship="romantic" direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes" type="external" felt="lament">Andromache led the wailing,</emotion>
 holding in her arms the while the head of <character who="Hector" epithet="negative">man-slaying Hector</character>:<lb/>"Husband, perished from out of
 life art thou, <emotion felt="lament" type="external" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic">yet in thy youth, and leavest me a widow in thy halls; and thy son is still but a
 babe, the son born of thee and me in our haplessness; neither do I deem that he will come to
 manhood, for ere that shall this city be wasted utterly,</emotion></action>. For thou hast perished that didst watch
 thereover,<lb/>thou that didst guard it, and keep safe its noble wives and little children. These,
 I ween, shall soon be riding upon the hollow ships, and I among them; and thou, my child, shalt
 follow with me to a place where thou shalt labour at unseemly tasks, toiling before the face of
 some ungentle master, or else some Achaean shall seize thee by the arm<lb/>and hurl thee from the
 wall, a woeful death,</emotion> being wroth for that <character who="Hector" >Hector</character> slew his brother haply, or his father, or his
 son, seeing that full many Achaeans at the hands of <character who="Hector">Hector</character> have bitten the vast earth with their
 teeth; for nowise gentle was thy father in woeful war.<lb/>Therefore the folk wail for him
 throughout the city, and grief unspeakable and sorrow hast thou brought upon thy parents, <character who="Hector">Hector</character>;
 and for me beyond all others shall grievous woes be left. For at thy death thou didst neither
 stretch out thy hands to me from thy bed, nor speak to me any word of wisdom whereon<lb/>I might
 have pondered night and day with shedding of tears."<lb/> So spake she wailing, and thereat the
 women made lament. And among them Hecabe in turns led the vehement wailing:"<character who="Hector">Hector</character>, far dearest to
 my heart of all my children, lo, when thou livedst thou wast dear to the gods,<lb/>and therefore
 have they had care of thee for all thou art in the doom of death. For of other sons of mine
 whomsoever he took would swift-footed <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> sell beyond the unresting sea, unto Samos and Imbros
 and Lemnos, shrouded in smoke, but, when from thee he had taken away thy life with the long-edged
 bronze<lb/>oft would he drag thee about the barrow of his comrade, <character who="Patroclus"> Patroclus </character>, whom thou didst slay;
 howbeit even so might he not raise him up. all dewy-fresh thou liest in my halls as wert thou g
 newly slain, like as one whom Apollo of the silver bow assaileth with his gentle shafts and
 slayeth." <lb/><action relationship="romantic" direction="at_someone" setting="public" intention="positive">So spake she wailing, and roused unabating lament</action>. <emotion direction="at_someone" relationship="familial" appropriate="yes" type="external" felt="lament">And thereafter Helen was the
 third to lead the wailing:</emotion>"<character who="Hector">Hector</character>, far dearest to my heart of all my husband's brethren! In sooth
 my husband is godlike Alexander, that brought me to Troy-land —would I died ere then!<lb/>For this
 is now the twentieth year from the time when I went from thence and am gone from my native land,
 but never yet heard I evil or despiteful word from thee; nay, if so be any other spake
 reproachfully of me in the halls, a brother of thine or a sister, or brother's fair-robed
 wife,<lb/>or thy mother—but thy father was ever gentle as he had been mine own—yet wouldst thou
 turn them with speech and restrain them by the gentleness of thy spirit and thy gentle words.
 Wherefore I wail alike for thee and for my hapless self with grief at heart; for no longer have I
 anyone beside in broad Troy<lb/>that is gentle to me or kind; but all men shudder at me."<lb/> So
 spake she wailing, and thereat the countless throng made moan. But the old man <character who="Priam">Priam</character> spake among
 the folk, saying:<action relationship="familial" direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">"Bring wood now, ye men of Troy, unto the city, neither have ye anywise fear at
 heart of a cunning ambush of the Argives; for verily <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> laid upon me this word<lb/>when he
 sent me forth from the black ships, that he would do us no hurt until the twelfth dawn be come." So
 spake he, and they yoked oxen and mules to waggons, and speedily thereafter gathered together
 before the city. For nine days' space they brought in measureless store of wood,<lb/>but when the
 tenth Dawn arose, giving light unto mortals, then bare they forth <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">bold Hector</character>, shedding tears the
 while, and on the topmost pyre they laid the dead man, and cast fire thereon.</action> <action setting="public" intention="positive" direction="at_someone" relationship="familial">But soon as early
 <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">Dawn appeared, the rosy-fingered</character>, then gathered the folk about the pyre of <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">glorious Hector</character>.<lb/>And
 when they were assembled and met together, first they quenched with flaming wine all the pyre, so
 far as the fire's might had come upon it, and thereafter his brethren and his comrades gathered the
 white bones, mourning, and big tears flowed ever down their cheeks.<lb/>The bones they took and
 placed in a golden urn, covering them over with soft purple robes, and quickly laid the urn in a
 hollow grave, and covered it over with great close-set stones. </action><action intention="positive" direction="at_no-one" setting="public" relationship="familial">Then with spe'[ed heaped they the
 mound, and round about were watchers set on every side,<lb/>lest the well-greaved Achaeans should
 set upon them before the time. And when they had piled the barrow they went back, and gathering
 together duly feasted a glorious feast in the palace of <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">Priam, the king fostered of </character><character who="Gods">Zeus</character>.</action><action intention="positive" relationship="familial" setting="public" direction="at_someone"> On this
 wise held they funeral for <character who="Hector" epithet="neutral">horse-taming Hector</character></emotion></action>.</action></book>
