<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<book>
                    <lb/>for slowest of all were his
                    fair-maned horses, and himself least skilled to drive a chariot in the race. And
                    the <character>son of Admetus</character> came in last, behind all the rest, <action>dragging his fair chariot</action>
                    and driving his horses before him. And at sight of him <epithet>swift-footed, goodly</epithet>
                   <character>Achilles</character> had <emotion>pity</emotion><lb/>and <action>he stood up</action> amid <character>the
                    Argives</character>, and <action>spake winged words</action>: "Lo, in the last place driveth his
                        single-hooved horses the man that is far the best. But come, let us give him
                        a prize, as is meet, a prize for the second place; but the first let the son
                        of Tydeus bear away." So spake he, and <action>they all assented</action> even as he
                        bade.<lb/>And now would he have given him
                    the mare —for <character>the Achaeans</character> assented thereto —but that <character>Antilochus, son of
                    <epithet>great-souled</epithet> Nestor</character>, uprose and answered <character>Achilles</character>, <epithet>son of Peleus</epithet>, to claim his
                    due: "<character>Achilles</character>, <emotion>sore wroth shall I be</emotion> with thee if thou fulfill this word,
                        for thou art <action>minded to rob me</action> of my prize,<lb/>bethinking thee of this, how his chariot and his swift
                        honses came to harm, and himself withal, good man though he be. Nay, he
                        should have made prayer to the immortals, then had he nowise come in last of
                        all in the race. But if so be thou <emotion>pitiest him</emotion>, and <relationship>he be dear</relationship> to thy heart,
                        lo, in thy hut is great store of gold, and bronze is there<lb/>and sheep, aye, and handmaids too, and single-hooved
                        horses. Thereof do thou hereafter <action>take and give him even a goodlier prize</action>,
                        or even now forthwith, that <character>the Achaeans</character> may applaud thee. But the mare will
                        not yield; for her let any man that will, essay to do battle with me by
                        might of hand."<lb/>
                    <lb/>So spake he , and <epithet>swift-footed, goodly</epithet>
                   <character>Achilles</character> smiled, <emotion>having joy</emotion> in <character>Antilochus</character>, for that he was his <relationship>dear comrade</relationship>; and
                    he made answer, and <action>spake to him winged words</action>:"<character>Antilochus</character>, if thou wilt
                        have men give to <character>Eumelus</character> some other thing from out my house as a further
                        prize, even this will I do.<lb/>I will
                        give him the corselet that I took from <character>Asteropaeus</character>; of bronze is it, and
                        thereon is set in circles a casting of bright tin, and it shall be to him a
                        thing of great worth." He spake, and bade his dear comrade Automedon
                    bring it from the hut and he went and brought it,<lb/>and placed it in Eumelus' hands and he received it gladly. Then
                    among them uprose also Menelaus, sore vexed at heart, furiously wroth at
                    Antilochus; and a herald gave the staff into his hand, and proclaimed silence
                    among the Argives; and thereafter spake among them the godlike man: <lb/>"Antilochus, thou that aforetime wast
                        wise, what a thing hast thou wrought! Thou hast put my skill to shame and
                        hast thwarted my horses, thrusting to the front thine own that were worser
                        far. Come now, ye leaders and rulers of the Argives, judge ye aright betwixt
                        us twain, neither have regard unto either,<lb/>lest in aftertime some one of the brazen-coated Achaeans
                        shall say: ‘Over Antilochus did Menelaus prevail by lies, and depart with
                        the mare, for that his horses were worser far, but himself the mightier in
                        worth and in power.’ Nay, but I will myself declare the right, and I deem
                            that<lb/>none other of the Danaans
                        shall reproach me, for my judgement shall be just. Antilochus, fostered of
                        Zeus, up, come thou hither and, as is the appointed way, stand thou before
                        thy horses and chariot, and take in hand the slender lash with which
                        aforetimethou wast wont to drive, and laying thy hand on thy horses swear by
                        him that holdeth and shaketh the earth<lb/>that not of thine own will didst thou hinder my chariot by guile."
                    <lb/> Then in turn wise Antilochus answered
                    him: "Bear with me, now, for far younger am I than thou, king Menelaus,
                        and thou art the elder and the better man. Thou knowest of what sort are the
                        transgressions of a man that he is young,<lb/>for hasty is he of purpose and but slender is his wit.
                        Wherefore let thy heart be patient; the mare that I have won will I give
                        thee of my self. Aye, and if thou shouldst ask some other goodlier thing
                        from out my house, forthwith were I fain to give it thee out of hand, rather
                        than all my days be cast out of thy heart, thou nurtured of Zeus,<lb/>and be a sinner in the eyes of the
                        gods." So spake the son of great-souled Nestor, and led up the mare,
                    and gave her into the hands of Menelaus. And his heart was gladdened even as the
                    corn when with the dew upon the ears it waxeth ripe, what time the fields are
                        bristling.<lb/>In such wise, Menelaus, was
                    thy heart gladdened in thy breast. Then he spake winged words unto Antilochos,
                    saying: "Antilochus, lo now, I of myself cease from mine anger against
                        thee, since nowise flighty or light of wit wast thou of old, albeit now hath
                        thy youth got the better of thy reason.<lb/>Another time seek not to outwit thy betters. Verily not soon should
                        another of the Achaeans have persuaded me, but thou hast suffered greatly
                        and toiled greatly, thou and thy brave father and thy brother, for my sake;
                        wherefore I will hearken to thy prayer, aye,<lb/>and will give unto thee the mare, for all she is mine own,
                        to the end that these too may know that my heart is never over-haughty
                        neither unbending." He spake, and gave the mare unto Nosmon, the
                    comrade of Antilochus, to lead away, and himself thereafter took the shining
                    cauldron. And Meriones took up the two talents of gold in the fourth
                        place,<lb/>even as he drave; but the fifth
                    prize was left unclaimed, even the two-handled urn. Unto Nestor Achilles gave
                    this, bearing it through the gathering of the Argives; and he came to his side,
                    and said"Take this now, old sire, and let it be treasure for thee, a
                        memorial of Patroclus' burying; for nevermore shalt thou behold
                            him<lb/>among the Argives. Lo, I give
                        thee this prize unwon; for not in boxing shalt thou contend, neither in
                        wrestling, nor shalt thou enter the lists for the casting of javelins,
                        neither run upon thy feet; for now grievous old age weigheth heavy upon
                        thee."
                    <lb/> So saying he placed the urn in his arms,
                    and Nestor received it gladly,<lb/>and spake,
                    and addressed him with winged words :"Aye, verily, my son, all this hast
                        thou spoken aright, for my limbs, even my feet, are no more firm, O my
                        friend, as of old, nor do my arms as of old dart out lightly from my
                        shoulders on either side. Would that I were young, and my strength were
                            firm<lb/>as on the day when the
                        Epeians were burying lord Amarynceus at Buprasium, and his sons appointed
                        prizes in honour of the king. Then was there no man that proved himself my
                        peer, neither of the Epeians nor of Pylians themselves nor of the
                        great-souled Aetolians. In boxing I overcame Clytomedes, son of
                            Enops,<lb/>and in wrestling Ancaeus of
                        Pleuron, who stood up against me; Iphiclus I outran in the foot-race, good
                        man though he was; and in casting the spear I outthrew Phyleus and
                        Polydorus. In the chariot race alone the twain sons of Actor outstripped me
                        by force of numbers crowding their horses to the front, being exceeding
                        jealous for victory,<lb/>for that the
                        goodliest prize abode yet there in the lists. Twin brethren were they— the
                        one drave with sure hand, drave with sure hand, while the other plied the
                        goad. Thus was I on a time, but now let men that be younger face such-like
                        tasks; me it behoveth to yield to grievous old age,<lb/>but then was I pre-eminent among warriors. But come, for
                        thy comrade too hold thou funeral rites with contests. For this gift, I
                        receive it wlth gladness, and my heart rejoiceth that thou rememberest me,
                        thy friend, neither am I forgotten of thee, and the honour wherewith it
                        beseemeth that I be honoured among the Achaeans.<lb/>And to thee may the gods in requital thereof grant grace to
                        satisfy thy heart." So spake he, and the son of Peleus went his way
                    through the great throng of the Achaeans, when he had hearkened to all the
                    praise of the son of Neleus. Then set he forth prizes for grievous boxing. A
                    sturdy mule he brought and tethered in the place of gathering,<lb/>a mule of six years, unbroken, the which is hardest of
                    all to break; and for him that should be worsted he appointed a two-handled cup.
                    Then he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying: "Son of Atreus, and
                        ye other well-greaved Achaeans, for these prizes we invite warriors twain,
                        the best there are, to lift up their hands and box amain.<lb/>Let him to whom Apollo shall grant strength to
                        endure, and all the Achaeans have knowledge thereof, go his way to his hut
                        leading the sturdy muIe; but he that is worsted shall bear as his prize the
                        two-handled cup."<lb/> So spake he,
                    and forthwith uprose a man valiant and tall,<lb/>well-skilled in boxing, even Epeius, son of Panopeus; and he
                    laid hold of the sturdy mule, and spake, saying:"Let him draw nigh, whoso
                        is to bear as his prize the two-handled cup : the mule I deem that none
                        other of the Achaeans shall lead away, by worsting me with his fists, for I
                        avow me to be the best man.<lb/>Sufficeth
                        it not that I fall short in battle? One may not, meseemeth, prove him a man
                        of skill in every work. For thus will I speak, and verily this thing shall
                        be brought to pass : utterly will I rend his flesh and crush his bones.
                        Wherefore let them that be next of kin abide here in a throng,<lb/>that they may bear him forth when worsted by
                        my hands." So spake he, and they all became hushed in silence.
                    Euryalus alone uprose to face him, a godlike man, son of king Mecisteus, son of
                    Talaus, who on a time had come to Thebes for the burial of Oedipus,<lb/>when he had fallen, and there had worsted all
                    the sons of Cadmus. And Tydeus' son, famed for his spear, made Euryalus ready,
                    heartening him with words, and much he wished for him victory. A girdle first he
                    cast about him, and thereafter gave him well-cut thongs of the hide of an ox of
                    the field.<lb/>So the twain, when they had
                    girded themselves, stepped into the midst of the place of gathering, and lifting
                    their mighty hands on high one against the other, fell to, and their hands
                    clashed together in heavy blows. Dread then was the grinding of their teeth, and
                    the sweat flowed on every side from off their limbs But upon him goodly Epeius
                        rushed<lb/>as he peered for an opening,and
                    smote him on the cheek, nor after that, methinks, did he long stand upright, for
                    even there did his glorious limbs sink beneath him. And as when beneath the
                    ripple of the North Wind a fish leapeth up on the tangle-strewn sand of a
                    shallow, and then the black wave hideth it, even so leapt up Euryalus when he
                    was smitten. But great-souled Epeius<lb/>took
                    him in his hands and set him on his feet, and his dear comrades thronged about
                    him and led him through the place of gathering with trailing feet, spitting out
                    clotted blood and letting his head hang to one side; and they brought him
                    wandering in his wits and set him down in the midst of their company, and
                    themselves went and fetched the two-handled cup.<lb/>
                    <lb/>Then the son of Peleus forthwith ordained
                    in the sight of the Danaans other prizes for a third contest, even for toilsome
                    wrestling — for him that should win, a great tripod to stand upon the fire, that
                    the Achaeans prized amongst them at the worth of twelve oxen; and for him that
                    should be worsted he set in the midst a woman<lb/>of manifold skill in handiwork, and they prized her at the
                    worth of four oxen. And he stood up and spake among the Argives saying:"Up
                        now, ye twain that will make essay likewise in this contest." So
                    spake he, and thereat arose great Telamonian Aias, and up stood Odysseus of many
                    wiles, he of guileful mind.<lb/>Then the
                    twain, when they had girded themselves, stepped into the midst of the place of
                    gathering, and laid hold each of the other in close grip with their mighty
                    hands, even as the gable-rafters of a high house, which some famous craftsman
                    joineth together, that he may have shelter from the might of the winds. And
                    their backs creaked beneath the violent tugging of bold hands,<lb/>and the sweat flowed down in streams; and many a weal,
                    red with blood, sprang up along their ribs and shoulders; and ever they strove
                    amain for victory, to win the fashioned tripod. Neither might Odysseus avail to
                    trip Aias and throw him to the ground,<lb/>nor
                    Aias him, for the mighty strength of Odysseus held firm. But when at the last
                    they were like to weary the well-greaved Achaeans, then unto Odysseus spake
                    great Telamonian Aias, saying:"Zeus-born, son of Laertes, Odysseus of many
                        wiles, lift thou me, or let me lift thee; but the issue shall rest with
                        Zeus."
                    <lb/>He spake, and lifted him; but Odysseus
                    forgat not his guile. He smote with a sure blow the hollow of Aias' knee from
                    behind, and loosed his limbs, so that he was thrown backward, and Odysseus fell
                    upon his chest; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with wonder. Then
                    in his turn the much-enduring goodly Odysseus essayed to lift,<lb/>and moved him a little from the ground, but lifted him
                    not, howbeit he crooked his knee within that of Aias, and upon the ground the
                    twain fell one hard by the other, and were befouled with dust. And now would
                    they have sprung up again for the third time and have wrestled, but that
                    Achilles himself uprose, and held them back:<lb/>"No longer strain ye now, neither be worn with pain.
                        Victory is with you both; take then equa1 prizes and go your ways, that
                        other Achaeans too may strive." So spake he, and they readily
                    hearkened to him and obeyed, and wiping from their bodies the dust they put upon
                    them their tunics.<lb/>
                    <lb/>Then the son of Peleus straightway set
                    forth other prizes for fleetness of foot: a mixingbowl of silver, richly
                    wrought; six measures it held, and in beauty it was far the goodliest in all the
                    earth, seeing that Sidonians, well skilled in deft handiwork, had wrought it
                    cunningly, and men of the Phoenicians brought it over the murky deep, and landed
                    it in harbour,<lb/>and gave it as a gift to
                    Thoas; and as a ransom for Lycaon, son of Priam, Jason's son Euneos gave it to
                    the warrior Patroclus. This bowl did Achilles set forth as a prize in honourof
                    his comrade, even for him whoso should prove fleetest in speed of
                        foot.<lb/>For the second again he set an
                    ox great and rich with fat; and a half-talent in gold he appointed for the last.
                    And he stood up, and spake among the Argives saying: "Up now, ye that will
                        make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and forthwith
                    uprose swift Aias, son of Oïleus,<lb/>and
                    Odysseus of many wiles, and after them Antilochus, Nestor's son, for he
                    surpassed all the youths in swiftness of foot. Then took they their places in a
                    row, and Achilles showed them the goal, and a course was marked out for them
                    from the turning-point. Then speedily the son of Oïleus forged to the front, and close
                    after him sped goodly Odysseus;<lb/>close as
                    is the weaving-rod to the breast of a fair-girdled woman, when she deftly
                    draweth it in her hands, pulling the spool past the warp, and holdeth the rod
                    nigh to her breast; even so close behind ran Odysseus,<lb/>and his feet trod in the footsteps of Aias or ever the dust had
                    settled therein, and down upon his head beat the breath of goodly Odysseus, as
                    he ran ever swiftly on; and all the Achaeans shouted to further him as he
                    struggled for victory, and called to him as he strained to the utmost. But when
                    now they were running the last part of the course, straightway Odysseus made
                    prayer in his heart to flashing-eyed Athene:<lb/>"Hear me, goddess, and come a goodly helper to my
                        feet." So spake he in prayer, and Pallas Athene heard him, and made
                    his limbs light, his feet and his hands above. But when they were now about to
                    dart forth to win the prize, then Aias slipped as he ran—for Athene hampered
                        him—<lb/>where was strewn the filth from
                    the slaying of the loud bellowing bulls that swift-footed Achilles had slain in
                    honour of Patroclus; and with the filth of the bulls were his mouth and nostrils
                    filled. So then much-enduring, goodly Odysseus took up the bowl, seeing he came
                    in the first, and glorious Aias took the ox.<lb/>And he stood holding in his hands the horn of the ox of the
                    field, spewing forth the filth; and he spake among the Argives: "Out upon
                        it, lo, the goddess hampered me in my running, she that standeth ever by
                        Odysseus' side like a mother, and helpeth him."<lb/> So spake he, but they all laughed merrily at
                        him.<lb/>Then Antilochus bare away the
                    last prize, smiling the while, and spake among the Argives, saying: "Among
                        you all that know it well, will I declare, my friends, that even to this day
                        the immortals shew honour to older men. For Aias is but a little older than
                            I,<lb/>whereas Odysseus is of an
                        earlier generation and of earlier men—a green old age is his, men say—yet
                        hard were he for any other Achaean to contend with in running, save only for
                        Achilles." So spake he,and gave glory to the son of Peleus, swift of
                    foot. And Achilles made answer, and spake to him, saying:<lb/>"Antilochus, not in vain shall thy word of praise
                        be spoken; nay, I will add to thy prize a half-talent of gold." So
                    saying, he set it in his hands, and Antilochus received it gladly. But the son
                    of Peleus brought and set in the place of gathering a far-shadowing spear, and
                    therewith a shield and helmet,<lb/>the
                    battlegear of Sarpedon, that Patroclus stripped from him; and he stood up, and
                    spake among the Argives, saying:"To win these prizes invite we warriors
                        twain, the best there are, to clothe them in their armour and take bronze
                        that cleaveth the flesh, and so make trial each of the other before the
                            host.<lb/>Whoso of the twain shall
                        first reach the other's fair flesh, and touch the inward parts through
                        armour and dark blood, to him will I give this silver-studded sword—a goodly
                        Thracian sword which I took from Asteropaeus; and these arms let the twain
                        bear away to hold in common;<lb/>and a
                        goodly banquet shall we set before them in our huts." So spake he,
                    and thereat arose great Telamonian Aias, and up rose the son of Tydeus, stalwart
                    Diomedes. So when they had armed them on either side of the throng, into the
                    midst strode the twain, eager for battle,<lb/>glaring terribly; and amazement held all the Achaeans. But when they were come
                    near as they advance done against the other, thrice they set upon each other,
                    and thrice they clashed together. Then Aias thrust upon the shield, that was
                    well-balanced upon every side, but reached not the flesh, for the corselet
                    within kept off the spear.<lb/>But Tydeus' son
                    over the great shield sought ever to reach the neck with the point of his
                    shining spear, Then verily the Achaeans, seized with fear for Aias, bade them
                    cease and take up equal prizes. Howbeit to Tydeus' son the warrior gave the
                    great sword,<lb/>bringing it with its scabbard
                    and its well-cut baldric.<lb/> Then the son of
                    Peleus set forth a mass of rough-cast iron, which of old the mighty strength of
                    Eëtion was wont to hurl; but him had swift-footed goodly Achilles slain, and
                    bare this away on his ships with his other possessions.<lb/>And he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying :"Up
                        now, ye that will make essay likewise in this contest. Though his rich
                        fields lie very far remote, the winner hereof will have it five revolving
                        years to serve his need; for not through lack of iron will his shepherd or
                            ploughman<lb/>fare to the city; nay,
                        this will supply them." So spake he, and thereat arose Polypoetes,
                    staunch in fight, and the mighty strength of godlike Leonteus, and Aias, son of
                    Telamon, and goodly Epeius. Then they took their places in order, and goodly
                    Epeius grasped the mass,<lb/>and whirled and
                    flung it; and all the Achaeans laughed aloud thereat. Then in turn Leonteus,
                    scion of Ares, made a cast; and thirdly great Telamonian Aias hurled it from his
                    strong hand, and sent it past the marks of all. But when Polypoetes, staunch in
                        fight,<lb/>grasped the mass, far as a
                    herdsman flings his crook, and it flieth whirling over the herds of kine, even
                    so far cast he it beyond all the gathering; and the folk shouted aloud. And the
                    comrades of strong Polypoetes rose up and bare to the hollow ships the prize of
                    the king. <lb/>Then for the archers he set
                    forth as a prize dark iron—ten double axes laid he down, and ten single; and he
                    set up the mast of a dark-prowed ship far off in the sands, and with a slender
                    cord made fast thereto by the foot a timorous dove, and bade shoot
                        thereat.<lb/>"Whoso shall hit the
                        timorous dove let him take up all the double axes and bear them home, and
                        whoso shall hit the cord, albeit he miss the bird: lo, his is the worser
                        shot; he shall bear as his prize the single axes."<lb/> So spake he, and there arose the might of the prince
                        Teucer,<lb/>and Meriones the valiant
                    squire of Idomeneus. Then took they the lots and shook them in a helmet of
                    bronze, and Teucer drew by lot the first place. Forthwith he let fly an arrow
                    with might, howbeit he vowed not that he would sacrifice to the king a glorious
                    hecatomb of firstling lambs.<lb/>So he missed
                    the bird, for Apollo grudged him that, but hit the cord beside its foot
                    wherewith the bird was tied, and clean away the bitter arrow cut the cord. Then
                    the dove darted skyward, and the cord hung loose toward earth; and the Achaeans
                    shouted aloud.<lb/>But Meriones speedily
                    snatched the bow from Teucer's hand—an arrow had he long been holding while
                    Teucer aimed—and vowed forthwith that he would sacrifice to Apollo that smiteth
                    afar a glorious hecatomb of firstling lambs. High up beneath the cloud he spied
                    the timorous dove;<lb/>there as she circled
                    round he struck her in the midst beneath the wing, and clean through passed the
                    shaft, and fell again and fixed itself in the ground before the foot of
                    Meriones; but the dove, lighting on the mast of the dark-prowed ship, hung down
                    her head, and her thick plumage drooped.<lb/>Swiftly the life fled from her limbs, and she fell far from the mast; and the
                    people gazed thereon and were seized with wonder. And Meriones took up all ten
                    double axes, and Teucer bare the single to the hollow ships. Then the son of
                    Peleus brought and set in the place of gathering a far-shadowing spear<lb/>and a cauldron, that the fire had not yet
                    touched, of an ox's worth, embossed with flowers; and men that were hurlers of
                    javelins arose. Up rose the son of Atreus, wide-ruling Agamemnon and Meriones,
                    the valiant squire of Idomeneus. But among them spake swift-footed, goodly
                        Achilles:<lb/>"Son of Atreus, we
                        know how far thou excellest all, and how far thou art the best in might and
                        in the casting of the spear; nay, take thou this prize and go thy way to the
                        hollow ships; but the spear let us give to the warrior Meriones, if thy
                        heart consenteth thereto: so at least would I have it:"
                    <lb/>So spake he, and the king of men,
                    Agamemnon, failed not to hearken. Then to Meriones he gave the spear of bronze,
                    but the warrior handed to the herald Talthybius the beauteous prize.
</book>
