<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="UPDATEDSCHEMA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<book>
    <lb/>for slowest of all were his fair-maned horses, and himself least skilled to drive a chariot
    in the race. And the son of Admetus came in last, behind all the rest, <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">dragging his fair
        chariot</action> and driving his horses before him. And at sight of him <character
        who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly Achilles</character> had <emotion
        type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone"
    >pity</emotion><lb/>and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he
        stood up</action> amid the Argives, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">spake winged words</action>: "Lo, in the last place driveth his
    single-hooved horses the man that is far the best. But come, let us give him a prize, as is
    meet, a prize for the second place; but the first let the son of Tydeus bear away." So spake he,
    and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">they all
        assented</action> even as he bade.<lb/>And now would he have given him the mare —for the
    Achaeans assented thereto —but that Antilochus, son of great-souled Nestor, uprose and answered
        <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">Achilles, son of Peleus</character>, to claim
    his due: "<character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>, <emotion type="external" felt="wrath"
        appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone">sore wroth shall I be</emotion> with thee if thou
    fulfill this word, for thou art <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">minded to rob me</action> of my prize,<lb/>bethinking thee of this,
    how his chariot and his swift honses came to harm, and himself withal, good man though he be.
    Nay, <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">he should have made
        prayer to the immortals, then had he nowise come in last of all in the race.</action> But if
    so be thou <emotion type="external" felt="lament" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone"
        >pitiest him</emotion>, and he be dear to thy heart, lo, in thy hut is great store of gold,
    and bronze is there<lb/>and sheep, aye, and handmaids too, and single-hooved horses. Thereof do
    thou hereafter take and give him even a goodlier prize, or even now forthwith, that the Achaeans
    may applaud thee. But the mare will not yield; for her let any man that will, essay to do battle
    with me by might of hand."<lb/>
    <lb/>So spake he, and <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly
        Achilles</character> smiled, <emotion type="external" felt="relief" appropriate="yes"
        direction="at_someone" relationship="neutral">having joy</emotion> in Antilochus, for that
    he was his dear comrade; and he made answer, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">spake to him winged words</action>:"Antilochus, if thou wilt have men
    give to Eumelus some other thing from out my house as a further prize, even this will I
    do.<lb/>I will give him the corselet that I took from Asteropaeus; of bronze is it, and thereon
    is set in circles a casting of bright tin, and it shall be to him a thing of great worth."
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">He spake, and bade his
        dear comrade</action> Automedon bring it from the hut and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he went and brought it</action>,<lb/>and placed it in
    Eumelus' hands and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he
        received it gladly.</action> Then among them uprose also Menelaus, <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">sore vexed at heart, furiously
        wroth at Antilochus; and a herald gave the staff into his hand, and proclaimed silence among
        the Argives; and thereafter spake among them the godlike man:</action>
    <lb/>"Antilochus, thou that aforetime wast wise, what a thing hast thou wrought! Thou hast put
    my skill to shame and hast thwarted my horses, thrusting to the front thine own that were worser
    far. Come now, ye leaders and rulers of the Argives, judge ye aright betwixt us twain, neither
    have regard unto either,<lb/>lest in aftertime some one of the brazen-coated Achaeans shall say:
    ‘Over Antilochus did Menelaus prevail by lies, and depart with the mare, for that his horses
    were worser far, but himself the mightier in worth and in power.’ Nay, but I will myself declare
    the right, and I deem that<lb/>none other of the Danaans shall reproach me, for my judgement
    shall be just. Antilochus, fostered of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>, up, come thou
    hither and, as is the appointed way, stand thou before thy horses and chariot, and take in hand
    the slender lash with which aforetimethou wast wont to drive, and laying thy hand on thy horses
    swear by him that holdeth and shaketh the earth<lb/>that not of thine own will didst thou hinder
    my chariot by guile." <lb/> Then in turn <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">wise Antilochus answered him:</action> "Bear with me, now, for far
    younger am I than thou, king Menelaus, and thou art the elder and the better man. Thou knowest
    of what sort are the transgressions of a man that he is young,<lb/>for hasty is he of purpose
    and but slender is his wit. Wherefore let thy heart be patient; the mare that I have won will I
    give thee of my self. Aye, and if thou shouldst ask some other goodlier thing from out my house,
    forthwith were I fain to give it thee out of hand, rather than all my days be cast out of thy
    heart, thou nurtured of <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>,<lb/>and be a sinner in the eyes
    of the gods." So spake the son of great-souled Nestor, and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">led up the mare, and gave her into the hands of
        Menelaus.</action> And <emotion type="internal" felt="relief" appropriate="yes"
        direction="at_someone">his heart was gladdened</emotion> even as the corn when with the dew
    upon the ears it waxeth ripe, what time the fields are bristling.<lb/>In such wise, Menelaus,
    was thy heart gladdened in thy breast. Then <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">he spake winged words unto Antilochos</action>, saying: "Antilochus,
    lo now, I of myself cease from mine anger against thee, since nowise flighty or light of wit
    wast thou of old, albeit now hath thy youth got the better of thy reason.<lb/>Another time seek
    not to outwit thy betters. Verily not soon should another of the Achaeans have persuaded me, but
    thou hast suffered greatly and toiled greatly, thou and thy brave father and thy brother, for my
    sake; wherefore I will hearken to thy prayer, aye,<lb/>and will give unto thee the mare, for all
    she is mine own, to the end that these too may know that my heart is never over-haughty neither
    unbending." He spake, and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"
        >gave the mare unto Nosmon</action>, the comrade of Antilochus, to lead away, and himself
    thereafter <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">took the shining
        cauldron</action>. And <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one"
        >Meriones took up the two talents of gold</action> in the fourth place,<lb/>even as he
    drave; but the fifth prize was left unclaimed, even the two-handled urn. Unto Nestor Achilles
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">gave this</action>,
    bearing it through the gathering of the Argives; and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">he came to his side, and said</action>"Take this
    now, old sire, and let it be treasure for thee, a memorial of Patroclus' burying; for nevermore
    shalt thou behold him<lb/>among the Argives. Lo, I give thee this prize unwon; for not in boxing
    shalt thou contend, neither in wrestling, nor shalt thou enter the lists for the casting of
    javelins, neither run upon thy feet; for now grievous old age weigheth heavy upon thee." <lb/>
    So saying <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">he placed the urn
        in his arms</action>, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">Nestor received it gladly</action>,<lb/>and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">spake, and addressed him with
        winged words</action> :"Aye, verily, my son, all this hast thou spoken aright, for my limbs,
    even my feet, are no more firm, O my friend, as of old, nor do my arms as of old dart out
    lightly from my shoulders on either side. Would that I were young, and my strength were
    firm<lb/>as on the day when the Epeians were burying lord Amarynceus at Buprasium, and his sons
    appointed prizes in honour of the king. Then was there no man that proved himself my peer,
    neither of the Epeians nor of Pylians themselves nor of the great-souled Aetolians. In boxing I
    overcame Clytomedes, son of Enops,<lb/>and in wrestling Ancaeus of Pleuron, who stood up against
    me; Iphiclus I outran in the foot-race, good man though he was; and in casting the spear I
    outthrew Phyleus and Polydorus. In the chariot race alone the twain sons of Actor outstripped me
    by force of numbers crowding their horses to the front, being exceeding jealous for
    victory,<lb/>for that the goodliest prize abode yet there in the lists. Twin brethren were they—
    the one drave with sure hand, drave with sure hand, while the other plied the goad. Thus was I
    on a time, but now let men that be younger face such-like tasks; me it behoveth to yield to
    grievous old age,<lb/>but then was I pre-eminent among warriors. But come, for thy comrade too
    hold thou funeral rites with contests. <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">For this gift, I receive it wlth gladness, and my heart rejoiceth
        that thou rememberest me, thy friend, neither am I forgotten of thee, and the honour
        wherewith it beseemeth that I be honoured among the Achaeans.</action><lb/>And to thee may
    the gods in requital thereof grant grace to satisfy thy heart." So spake he, and <character
        who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">the son of Peleus</character> went his way through the
    great throng of the Achaeans, when he <action direction="at_someone" intention="positive"
        setting="public">had hearkened to all the praise</action> of the son of Neleus. Then set
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he forth prizes</action>
    for grievous boxing. A sturdy mule he brought and tethered in the place of gathering,<lb/>a mule
    of six years, unbroken, the which is hardest of all to break; and for him that should be worsted
    he appointed a two-handled cup. Then he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying: "Son of
    Atreus, and ye other well-greaved Achaeans, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">for these prizes we invite warriors twain, the best there are, to
        lift up their hands and box amain.</action><lb/>Let him to whom <character who="Gods"
        >Apollo</character> shall grant strength to endure, and all the Achaeans have knowledge
    thereof, go his way to his hut leading the sturdy muIe; but he that is worsted shall bear as his
    prize the two-handled cup."<lb/> So spake he, and forthwith <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">uprose a man valiant and
    tall</action>,<lb/>well-skilled in boxing, even Epeius, son of Panopeus; and <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he laid hold of the sturdy mule,
        and spake,</action> saying:"Let him draw nigh, whoso is to bear as his prize the two-handled
    cup : the mule I deem that none other of the Achaeans shall lead away, by worsting me with his
    fists, for I avow me to be the best man.<lb/>Sufficeth it not that I fall short in battle? One
    may not, meseemeth, prove him a man of skill in every work. For thus will I speak, and verily
    this thing shall be brought to pass : <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">utterly will I rend his flesh and crush his bones.</action> Wherefore
    let them that be next of kin abide here in a throng,<lb/>that they may bear him forth when
    worsted by my hands." So spake he, and <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">they all became hushed in silence.</action> Euryalus alone <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">uprose to face him</action>, a
    godlike man, son of king Mecisteus, son of Talaus, who on a time had come to Thebes for the
    burial of Oedipus,<lb/>when he had fallen, and there had worsted all the sons of Cadmus. And
    Tydeus' son, famed for his spear, made Euryalus ready, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">heartening him with words, and much he wished for
        him victory.</action> A girdle first he cast about him, and thereafter gave him well-cut
    thongs of the hide of an ox of the field.<lb/>So the twain, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">when they had girded themselves, stepped into the
        midst of the place of gathering, and lifting their mighty hands on high one against the
        other, fell to, and their hands clashed together in heavy blows. Dread then was the grinding
        of their teeth, and the sweat flowed on every side from off their limbs</action> But upon
    him <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">goodly Epeius
        rushed</action><lb/>as he peered for an opening,and smote him on the cheek, nor after that,
    methinks, did he long stand upright, for even there did <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">his glorious limbs sink beneath him</action>. And as
    when beneath the ripple of the North Wind a fish leapeth up on the tangle-strewn sand of a
    shallow, and then the black wave hideth it, even so <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">leapt up Euryalus when he was smitten</action>. But
    great-souled Epeius<lb/><action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"
        >took him in his hands and set him on his feet, and his dear comrades thronged about him and
        led him through the place of gathering with trailing feet, spitting out clotted blood and
        letting his head hang to one side; and they brought him wandering in his wits and set him
        down in the midst of their company, and themselves went and fetched the two-handled
        cup.</action><lb/>
    <lb/>Then the son of Peleus forthwith <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">ordained in the sight of the Danaans other prizes for a third contest,
        even for toilsome wrestling</action> — for him that should win, a great tripod to stand upon
    the fire, that the Achaeans prized amongst them at the worth of twelve oxen; and for him that
    should be worsted he set in the midst a woman<lb/>of manifold skill in handiwork, and they
    prized her at the worth of four oxen. And <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">he stood up and spake among the Argives saying</action>:"Up now, ye
    twain that will make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">thereat arose great Telamonian
        Aias, and up stood Odysseus of many wiles, he of guileful mind.</action><lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">Then the twain, when they had
        girded themselves, stepped into the midst of the place of gathering, and laid hold each of
        the other in close grip with their mighty hands, even as the gable-rafters of a high house,
        which some famous craftsman joineth together, that he may have shelter from the might of the
        winds.</action>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">And their backs creaked
        beneath the violent tugging of bold hands</action>,<lb/><action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">and the sweat flowed down in streams; and many a
        weal, red with blood, sprang up along their ribs and shoulders; and ever they strove amain
        for victory, to win the fashioned tripod.</action> Neither might Odysseus avail to trip Aias
    and throw him to the ground,<lb/>nor Aias him, for <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">the mighty strength of Odysseus held firm.</action> But when at the
    last they were like to weary the well-greaved Achaeans, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">then unto Odysseus spake great Telamonian Aias,
        saying</action>:"Zeus-born, son of Laertes, Odysseus of many wiles, lift thou me, or let me
    lift thee; but the issue shall rest with <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>." <lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">He spake, and lifted him; but
        Odysseus forgat not his guile. He smote with a sure blow the hollow of Aias' knee from
        behind, and loosed his limbs, so that he was thrown backward, and Odysseus fell upon his
        chest; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with wonder.</action> Then in his turn
    the much-enduring goodly Odysseus essayed to lift,<lb/>and moved him a little from the ground,
    but lifted him not, howbeit he crooked his knee within that of Aias, <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">and upon the ground the twain
        fell one hard by the other, and were befouled with dust. And now would they have sprung up
        again for the third time and have wrestled,</action> but that <character who="Achilles"
        >Achilles</character> himself <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">uprose, and held them back</action>:<lb/>"No longer strain ye now,
    neither be worn with pain. Victory is with you both; take then equa1 prizes and go your ways,
    that other Achaeans too may strive." So spake he, and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">they readily hearkened to him and obeyed, and wiping
        from their bodies the dust they put upon them their tunics.</action><lb/>
    <lb/>Then <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">the son of Peleus</character> straightway
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">set forth other
        prizes</action> for fleetness of foot: a mixingbowl of silver, richly wrought; six measures
    it held, and in beauty it was far the goodliest in all the earth, seeing that Sidonians, well
    skilled in deft handiwork, had wrought it cunningly, and men of the Phoenicians brought it over
    the murky deep, and landed it in harbour,<lb/>and gave it as a gift to Thoas; and as a ransom
    for Lycaon, son of <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, Jason's son Euneos gave it to the
    warrior <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>. This bowl did <character
        who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one" relationship="romantic">set
        forth as a prize in honour of his comrade</action>, even for him whoso should prove fleetest
    in speed of foot.<lb/>For the second again <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">he set an ox great and rich with fat; and a half-talent in gold he
        appointed for the last.</action> And <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">he stood up, and spake among the Argives saying</action>: "Up now, ye
    that will make essay likewise in this contest." So spake he, and <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">forthwith uprose</action> swift Aias, son of
    Oïleus,<lb/>and Odysseus of many wiles, and after them Antilochus, Nestor's son, for he
    surpassed all the youths in swiftness of foot. <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">Then took they their places in a row, and Achilles showed them the
        goal, and a course was marked out for them from the turning-point.</action> Then speedily
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the son of Oïleus forged
        to the front, and close after him sped goodly Odysseus</action>;<lb/>close as is the
    weaving-rod to the breast of a fair-girdled woman, when she deftly draweth it in her hands,
    pulling the spool past the warp, and holdeth the rod nigh to her breast; even so close behind
    ran Odysseus,<lb/><action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">and his
        feet trod in the footsteps of Aias or ever the dust had settled therein, and down upon his
        head beat the breath of goodly Odysseus, as he ran ever swiftly on; and all the Achaeans
        shouted to further him as he struggled for victory, and called to him as he strained to the
        utmost.</action> But when now they were running the last part of the course, straightway
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">Odysseus made prayer in
        his heart</action> to <character who="Gods" epithet="positive">flashing-eyed
        Athene</character>:<lb/>"Hear me, goddess, and come a goodly helper to my feet." So spake he
    in prayer, and <character who="Gods">Pallas Athene</character> heard him, and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">made his limbs light, his feet
        and his hands above</action>. But when they were now about to dart forth to win the prize,
    then <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">Aias slipped as he
        ran</action>—for <character who="Gods">Athene</character>
    <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">hampered
    him</action>—<lb/>where was strewn the filth from the slaying of the loud bellowing bulls that
        <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed Achilles</character> had slain in
    honour of <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>; and with <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the filth of the bulls were his
        mouth and nostrils filled</action>. So then much-enduring, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">goodly Odysseus took up the bowl, seeing he came in
        the first</action>, and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one"
        >glorious Aias took the ox.</action><lb/>And <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">he stood holding in his hands the horn of the ox of the field, spewing
        forth the filth</action>; and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">he spake among the Argives</action>: "Out upon it, lo, <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">the goddess hampered me in my
        running</action>, she that standeth ever by Odysseus' side like a mother, and helpeth
    him."<lb/> So spake he, but <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone"
        >they all laughed merrily at him.</action><lb/>Then <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">Antilochus bare away the last prize, smiling the
        while, and spake among the Argives, saying</action>: "Among you all that know it well, will
    I declare, my friends, that even to this day <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">the immortals shew honour to older men.</action> For Aias is but a
    little older than I,<lb/>whereas Odysseus is of an earlier generation and of earlier men—a green
    old age is his, men say—yet hard were he for any other Achaean to contend with in running, save
    only for Achilles." So spake he, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">gave glory</action> to <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive"
        >the son of Peleus, swift of foot.</character> And <character who="Achilles"
        >Achilles</character> made answer, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">and spake to him, saying</action>:<lb/>"Antilochus, not in vain shall
    thy word of praise be spoken; nay, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">I will add to thy prize a half-talent of gold</action>." So saying,
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">he set it in his hands,
        and Antilochus received it gladly</action>. But <character who="Achilles" epithet="neutral"
        >the son of Peleus</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">brought and set in the
        place</action> of gathering a far-shadowing spear, and therewith a shield and
    helmet,<lb/>the battlegear of Sarpedon, that <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>
    stripped from him; and he stood up, and spake among the Argives, saying:"To win these prizes
    invite we warriors twain, the best there are, to clothe them in their armour and take bronze
    that cleaveth the flesh, and so make trial each of the other before the host.<lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">Whoso of the twain shall first
        reach the other's fair flesh, and touch the inward parts through armour and dark blood, to
        him will I give this silver-studded sword</action>—a goodly Thracian sword which I took from
    Asteropaeus; and these arms let the twain bear away to hold in common;<lb/>and a goodly banquet
    shall we set before them in our huts." So spake he, and thereat <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">arose great Telamonian Aias, and up rose the son of
        Tydeus, stalwart Diomedes</action>. So <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">when they had armed them on either side of the throng, into the midst
        strode the twain, eager for battle</action>,<lb/>glaring terribly; and amazement held all
    the Achaeans. But when they were come near as <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">they advance done against the other, thrice they set upon each other,
        and thrice they clashed together</action>. Then <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_someone">Aias thrust upon the shield</action>, that was
    well-balanced upon every side, but reached not the flesh, for the corselet within kept off the
    spear.<lb/>But Tydeus' son over the great shield <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">sought ever to reach the neck with the point of his shining
        spear</action>, Then verily the Achaeans, seized with fear for Aias, <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">bade them cease and take up
        equal prizes</action>. Howbeit to Tydeus' son the warrior gave the great sword,<lb/>bringing
    it with its scabbard and its well-cut baldric.<lb/> Then the <character who="Achilles"
        epithet="neutral">son of Peleus</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">set forth a mass of
        rough-cast iron</action>, which of old the mighty strength of Eëtion was wont to hurl; but
    him had <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed goodly Achilles</character>
    slain, and bare this away on his ships with his other possessions.<lb/><action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">And he stood up, and spake
        among the Argives</action>, saying :"Up now, ye that will make essay likewise in this
    contest. Though his rich fields lie very far remote, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the winner hereof will have it five revolving years
        to serve his need</action>; for not through lack of iron will his shepherd or
    ploughman<lb/>fare to the city; nay, this will supply them." So spake he, and <action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_someone">thereat arose Polypoetes,
        staunch in fight, and the mighty strength of godlike Leonteus, and Aias, son of Telamon, and
        goodly Epeius.</action> Then <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">they took their places in order</action>, and goodly Epeius grasped
    the mass,<lb/>and <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">whirled
        and flung it</action>; and <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">all the Achaeans laughed aloud</action> thereat. Then in turn
    Leonteus, scion of Ares,<action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">
        made a cast</action>; and thirdly great Telamonian Aias <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">hurled it from his strong hand, and sent it past the
        marks of all</action>. But when Polypoetes, staunch in fight,<lb/>grasped the mass, far as a
    herdsman flings his crook, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">it flieth whirling over the herds of kine, even so far cast he it
        beyond all the gathering; and the folk shouted aloud. And the comrades of strong Polypoetes
        rose up and bare to the hollow ships the prize of the king.</action>
    <lb/>Then <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">for the archers he
        set forth as a prize dark iron—ten double axes laid he down, and ten single; and he set up
        the mast of a dark-prowed ship far off in the sands, and with a slender cord made fast
        thereto by the foot a timorous dove, and bade shoot thereat.</action><lb/>"<action
        intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">Whoso shall hit the timorous
        dove let him take up all the double axes and bear them home, and whoso shall hit the cord,
        albeit he miss the bird: lo, his is the worser shot; he shall bear as his prize the single
        axes.</action>"<lb/> So spake he, and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">there arose</action> the might of the prince Teucer,<lb/>and Meriones
    the valiant squire of Idomeneus. <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">Then took they the lots and shook them in a helmet of bronze, and
        Teucer drew by lot the first place. Forthwith he let fly an arrow with might, howbeit he
        vowed not that he would sacrifice to the king a glorious hecatomb of firstling
        lambs.</action><lb/>So he <action intention="negative" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one"> missed the bird</action>, for <character who="Gods"
        >Apollo</character>
    <emotion appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone" felt="anger" relationship="neutral"
        type="external">grudged him</emotion> that, <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_no-one">but hit the cord beside its foot wherewith the bird was tied, and
        clean away the bitter arrow cut the cord. Then the dove darted skyward, and the cord hung
        loose toward earth;</action> and <action intention="positive" setting="public"
        direction="at_someone">the Achaeans shouted aloud</action>.<lb/>But Meriones <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_someone">speedily snatched the bow from
        Teucer's hand—an arrow had he long been holding while Teucer aimed</action>—and <action
        intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">vowed forthwith that he would
        sacrifice</action> to <character who="Gods">Apollo</character> that smiteth afar a glorious
    hecatomb of firstling lambs. High up beneath the cloud <action intention="negative"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he spied the timorous dove</action>;<lb/>there as she
    circled round <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">he struck her
        in the midst beneath the wing, and clean through passed the shaft, and fell again and fixed
        itself in the ground before the foot of Meriones; but the dove, lighting on the mast of the
        dark-prowed ship, hung down her head, and her thick plumage drooped.</action><lb/>Swiftly
        <action intention="negative" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">the life fled from her
        limbs, and she fell far from the mast; and the people gazed thereon and were seized with
        wonder.</action>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">And Meriones took up all ten
        double axes, and Teucer bare the single to the hollow ships.</action> Then <character
        who="Achilles" epithet="neutral">the son of Peleus</character>
    <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">brought and set in the place
        of gathering a far-shadowing spear</action><lb/>and a cauldron, that the fire had not yet
    touched, of an ox's worth, embossed with flowers; and men that were hurlers of javelins arose.
    Up rose the son of Atreus, <character who="Agamemnon" epithet="positive">wide-ruling
        Agamemnon</character> and Meriones, the valiant squire of Idomeneus. But among them spake
        <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">swift-footed, goodly
    Achilles</character>:<lb/>"Son of Atreus, we know how far thou excellest all, and how far thou
    art the best in might and in the casting of the spear; nay, <action intention="positive"
        setting="public" direction="at_no-one">take thou this prize and go thy way to the hollow
        ships; but the spear let us give to the warrior Meriones,</action> if thy heart consenteth
    thereto: so at least would I have it:" <lb/>So spake he, and <character who="Agamemnon"
        epithet="positive">the king of men, Agamemnon</character>, failed not to hearken. Then
        <action intention="positive" setting="public" direction="at_no-one">to Meriones he gave the
        spear of bronze, but the warrior handed to the herald Talthybius the beauteous
        prize.</action>
</book>
