<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-model href="UPDATEDSCHEMA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<book>
 <lb/><action intention="positive" direction="at_no-one" setting="public">Then was the gathering
  broken up, and the folk scattered, each man to go to his own ship. The rest bethought them of
  supper and of sweet sleep, to take their fill thereof</action>; but <character who="Achilles"
  >Achilles</character>
 <action intention="negative" direction="at_no-one" setting="private" relationship="romantic">wept,
  ever remembering his dear comrade</action>, neither might sleep,<lb/>that mastereth all, lay hold
 of him, but he turned him ever to this side or to that, <emotion direction="at_someone"
  appropriate="yes" felt="lament" relationship="romantic" type="internal">yearning for the man-hood
  and valorous might</emotion> of <character who="Patroclus">Patroclus</character>, thinking on all
 he had wrought with him and all the woes he had borne, passing though wars of men and the grievous
 waves. Thinking thereon <action intention="negative" direction="at_no-one" setting="private">he
  would shed big tears</action>,<lb/>lying now upon his side, now upon his back, and now upon his
 face; and then again <action intention="negative" direction="at_no-one" setting="private">he would
  rise upon his feet and roam distraught along the shore of the sea.</action> Neither would he fail
 to mark the Dawn, as she shone over the sea and the sea-beaches, but would yoke beneath the car his
 swift horses,<lb/>and bind <character who="Hector">Hector</character>
 <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public">behind the chariot to drag him
  withal; and when he had haled him thrice about the barrow of the dead son of Menoetius</action>,
 he would rest again in his hut, but would leave <character who="Hector">Hector</character>
 outstretched on his face in the dust. Howbeit <character who="Gods">Apollo</character>
 <action intention="positive" direction="at_someone" setting="public">kept all defacement from his
  flesh, pitying the warrior</action><lb/>even in death, and with the golden aegis he covered him
 wholly, that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> might not tear his body as he dragged
 him.<lb/> Thus <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> in his <emotion type="external"
  relationship="enemies" appropriate="yes" felt="wrath" direction="at_someone">fury</emotion> did
 foul despite unto <character who="Hector" epithet="positive">goodly Hector</character>; but the
 blessed gods had pity on him as they beheld him, and bestirred the keen-sighted Argeiphontes to
 steal away the corpse.<lb/>And the thing was pleasing unto all the rest, yet not unto <character
  who="Gods">Hera</character> or <character who="Gods">Poseidon</character> or the flashing-eyed
 maiden, but they continued even as when at the first sacred Ilios became hateful in their eyes and
  <character who="Priam">Priam</character> and his folk, by reason of the sin of Alexander, for that
 he put reproach upon those goddesses when they came to his steading,<lb/><action
  intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="public">and gave precedence to her who
  furthered his fatal lustfulness.</action> But when at length the twelfth morn thereafter was come,
 then <action intention="positive" direction="at_someone" setting="public">among the immortals
  spake</action>
 <character who="Gods">Phoebus Apollo</character>:"Cruel are ye, O ye gods, and workers of bane.
 Hath <character who="Hector">Hector</character> then never burned for you thighs of bulls and goats
 without blemish?<lb/>Him now have ye not the heart to save, a corpse though he be, for his wife to
 look upon and his mother and his child, and his father <character who="Priam">Priam</character> and
 his people, who would forthwith burn him in the fire and pay him funeral rites. Nay, it is
  <character who="Achilles" epithet="negative">the ruthless Achilles</character>, O ye gods, that ye
 are fain to succour,<lb/><emotion direction="at_someone" felt="anger" appropriate="yes"
  relationship="neutral" type="external">him whose mind is nowise right, neither the purpose in his
  breast one that may be bent; but his heart is set on cruelty,</emotion> even as a lion that at the
 bidding of his great might and lordly spirit goeth forth against the flocks of men to win him a
 feast; even so hath <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> lost all pity, neither is shame
 in his heart,<lb/>the which harmeth men greatly and profiteth them withal. Lo, it may be that a man
 hath lost one dearer even than was this—a brother, that the selfsame mother bare, or haply a son;
 yet verily when he hath wept and wailed for him he maketh an end; for an enduring soul have the
 Fates given unto men.<lb/>But this man, when he hath reft <character who="Hector"
  epithet="positive">goodly Hector</character> of life, bindeth him behind his chariot and draggeth
 him about the barrow of his dear comrade; in sooth neither honour nor profit shall he have
 therefrom. Let him beware lest we wax wroth with him, good man though he be; for lo, in his fury he
 doth foul despite unto senseless clay." <lb/>Then <emotion type="external" relationship="familial"
  appropriate="yes" felt="anger" direction="at_someone">stirred to anger</emotion> spake to him
  <character epithet="neutral" who="Gods"> white-armed Hera</character>:"Even this might be as thou
 sayest, Lord of the silver bow, if indeed ye gods will vouchsafe like honour to <character
  who="Achilles">Achilles</character> and to <character who="Hector">Hector</character>. <character
  who="Hector">Hector</character> is but mortal and was suckled at a woman's breast, but <character
  who="Achilles">Achilles</character> is the child of a goddess that I mine own self<lb/>fostered
 and reared, and gave to a warrior to be his wife, even to Peleus, who was heartily dear to the
 immortals. And all of you, O ye gods, came to her marriage, and among them thyself too didst sit at
 the feast, thy lyre in thy hand, O thou friend of evil-doers, faithless ever."<lb/> Then <character
  who="Gods" epithet="neutral">Zeus, the cloud-gatherer,</character>
 <action direction="at_someone" relationship="romantic" setting="public" intention="negative"
  >answered her</action>, and said:<lb/>"<character who="Gods">Hera</character>, be not thou utterly
 wroth against the gods; the honour of these twain shall not be as one; howbeit <character
  who="Hector">Hector</character> too was dearest to the gods of all mortals that are in Ilios. So
 was he to me at least, for nowise failed he of acceptable gifts. For never was my altar in lack of
 the equal feast,<lb/>the drink-offiering and the savour of burnt-offering, even the worship that is
 our due. Howbeit of the stealing away of bold <character who="Hector">Hector</character> will we
 naught; it may not be but that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> would be ware
 thereof; for verily his mother cometh ever to his side alike by night and day. But I would that one
 of the gods would call Thetis to come unto me,<lb/>that I may speak to her a word of wisdom, to the
 end that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> may accept gifts from <character
  who="Priam">Priam</character>, and give <character who="Hector">Hector</character> back." So spake
 he, and storm-footed Iris <action direction="at_no-one" intention="positive" setting="public"
  >hasted to bear his message</action>, and midway between Samos and rugged Imbros she leapt into
 the dark sea, and the waters sounded loud above her.<lb/>Down sped she to the depths hike a plummet
 of lead, the which, set upon the horn of an ox of the field, goeth down bearing death to the
 ravenous fishes. And she found Thetis in the hollow cave, and round about her other goddesses of
 the sea sat in a throng, and she in their midst<lb/>was wailing for the fate of her peerless son,
 who to her sorrow was to perish in deep-soiled Troy, far from his native land. And swift-footed
 Iris drew near, and spake to her:"Rouse thee, 0 Thetis; <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>,
 whose counsels are everlasting, calleth thee." Then spake in answer Thetis, the silver-footed
 goddess:<lb/>"Wherefore summoneth me that mighty god? I have shame to mingle in the company of the
 immortals, seeing I have measurehess griefs at heart. Howbeit I will go, neither shall his word be
 vain, whatsoever he shall speak."<lb/> So saying, the fair goddess took a dark-hued veil, than
 which was no raiment more black,<lb/>and<action direction="at_no-one" intention="positive"
  setting="public"> set out to go, and before her wind-footed swift Iris led the way</action>; and
 about them the surge of the sea parted asunder. And when they had stepped forth upon the beach they
 sped unto heaven; and they found the son of Cronos, whose voice is borne afar, and around him sat
 gathered together all the other blessed gods that are for ever.<lb/>Then she sate her down beside
 father <character who="Gods">Zeus</character>, and <character who="Gods">Athene</character> gave
 place. And <character who="Gods">Hera</character> set in her hand a fair golden cup, and spake
 words of cheer.; and Thetis drank, and gave back the cup. Then among them <action
  direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">the father of men and gods was first
  to speak</action>:"Thou art come to Olympus, 0, goddess Thetis,<lb/>for all thy sorrow, though
 thou hast comfortless grief at heart; I know it of myself; yet even so will I tell thee wherefore I
 called thee hither. For nine days' space hath strife arisen among the immortals as touching the
 corpse of <character who="Hector">Hector</character> and <character who="Achilles"
  epithet="negative">Achilles, sacker of cities</character>. They are for bestirring the
 keen-sighted Argeiphontes to steal the body away,<lb/>yet herein do I accord honour unto <character
  who="Achilles">Achilles</character>; for I would fain keep in time to come thy worship and thy
 love. Haste thee with all speed to the host and declare unto thy son my bidding. Say unto him
  <action direction="at_someone" intention="negative" setting="public">that the gods are angered
  with him</action>, and that <emotion direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes" type="external"
  felt="wrath">I above all immortals am filled with wrath</emotion>, for that in the fury of his
 heart<lb/>he holdeth <character who="Hector">Hector</character> at the beaked ships and gave him
 not back, if so be he may be seized with fear of me and give <character who="Hector"
  >Hector</character> back. But I will send forth Iris unto <character who="Priam"
  epithet="positive">great-hearted Priam</character>, to bid him go to the ships of the Achaeans to
 ransom his dear son, and <action direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">to
  bear gifts</action> unto <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart."<lb/>
 <lb/>So spake he, and the goddess, silver-footed Thetis, failed not to hearken, <action
  direction="at_no-one" intention="positive" setting="public">but went darting down from the peaks
  of Olympus, and came to the hut of her son.</action> There she found him <action
  direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">groaning ceaselessly</action>, and
 round about him his dear comrades with busy haste were making ready their early meal,<lb/>and in
 the hut a ram, great and shaggy, lay slaughtered for them. Then she,<action direction="at_someone"
  intention="positive" setting="public">his queenly mother, sate her down close by his side and
  stroked him with her hand, and spake, and called him by name</action>:"My child, how long wilt
 thou devour thine heart with weeping and sorrowing, and wilt take no thought of food,<lb/>neither
 of the couch? Good were it for thee even to have dalliance in a woman's embrace. For, I tell thee,
 thou shalt not thyself be long in life, but even now doth death stand hard by thee and mighty fate.
 But hearken thou forthwith unto me, for I am a messenger unto thee from Zeus. He declareth that
 that <emotion felt="anger" type="external" appropriate="yes" direction="at_someone">the gods are
  angered with thee</emotion>,<lb/>and that <emotion direction="at_someone" appropriate="yes"
  type="external" felt="wrath">himself above all immortals is filled with wrath</emotion>, for that
 in the fury of thine heart thou holdest <character who="Hector">Hector</character> at the beaked
 ships, and gavest him not back. Nay come, give him up, and take ransom for the dead." Then in
 answer to her spake <character who="Achilles" epithet="positive">Achilles, swift of
  foot</character>: "So let it be; whoso bringeth ransom, let him bear away the dead,<lb/>if verily
 with full purpose of heart the Olympian himself so biddeth." On this wise amid the gathering of the
 ships mother and son spake many winged words one to the other, but the son of Cronos sent forth
 Iris to sacred Ilios:"Up, go, swift Iris; leave thou the abode of Olympus<lb/>and bear tidings
 within Ilios unto <character epithet="positive" who="Priam">great-hearted Priam</character> that he
 go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom his dear son, and that <action direction="at_someone"
  intention="positive" setting="public">he bear gifts</action> unto <character who="Achilles"
  >Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart; alone let him go, neither let any man
 beside of the Trojans go with him. A herald may attend him, an elder man,<lb/>to guide the mules
 and the light-running waggon, and to carry back to the city the dead, even him that <character
  who="Achilles">Achilles</character> slew. Let not death be in his thoughts. neither any fear; such
 a guide will we give him, even Argeiphontes, who shall lead him, until in his leading he bring him
 nigh to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>.<lb/>And when he shall have led him into the
 hut, neither shall <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> himself slay him nor suffer any
 other to slay; for not without wisdom is he, neither without purpose, nor yet hardened in sin; nay,
 with all kindliness will he spare a suppliant man."<lb/> So spake he, and storm-footed Iris hasted
 to bear his message.<lb/>She came to the house of <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, and
 found therein <action direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">clamour and
  wailing</action>. His <action direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">sons
  sat about their father within the court sullying their garments with their tears, and in their
  midst was the old king close-wrapped in his mantle; and upon the old man's head and neck was filth
  in abundance</action>,<lb/>which he had gathered in his hands as he grovelled on the earth. And
  <action direction="at_no-one" intention="negative" setting="private">his daughters and his sons'
  wives were wailing throughout the house</action>, bethinking them of the warriors many and valiant
 who were lying low, slain by the hands of the Argives. And the messenger of Zeus drew nigh to
  <character who="Priam">Priam</character>, and spake to him;<lb/>softly she uttered her voice, yet
 trembling gat hold of his himbs:"Be of good courage, O <character who="Priam" epithet="neutral"
  >Priam, son of Dardanus</character>, and fear thou not at all. Not to forbode any evil to thee am
 I come hither, but with good intent. I am a messenger to thee from <character who="Gods"
  >Zeus</character>, who far away though he be, hath exceeding care for thee and pity.<lb/>The
 Olympian biddeth thee ransom goodly <character who="Hector">Hector</character>, and <action
  direction="at_someone" intention="positive" setting="public">bear gifts to</action>
 <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart; alone do thou go,
 neither let any man beside of the Trojans go with thee. A herald may attend thee, an elder man, to
 guide the mules and the light-running waggon,<lb/>and to carry back to the city the dead, even him
 that <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> slew. Let not death be in thy thoughts, neither
 any fear; such a guide shall go with thee, even Argeiphontes, who shall lead thee, until in his
 heading he bring thee nigh to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>. And when he shall
 have led thee into the hut,<lb/>neither shall <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
 himself slay thee nor suffer any other to slay; for not without wisdom is he, neither without
 purpose, nor yet hardened in sin; nay, with all kindliness will he spare a suppliant man." When she
 had thus spoken swift-footed Iris departed; but the king bade his sons<lb/>make ready the running
 mule waggon, and bind the wicker box thereon. And himself <action setting="private"
  intention="positive" direction="at_no-one">he went down to the vaulted treasure-chamber</action>,
 fragrant of cedar wood and high of roof, that held jewels full many: and he called to him Hecabe
 his wife, and spake:"Lady, from <character who="Gods">Zeus</character> hath an Olympian messenger
 come to me,<lb/>that I go to the ships of the Achaeans to ransom my dear son, and that I bear gifts
 to <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character> which shall make glad his heart. But come, tell
 me this, how seemeth it to thy mind? For as touching mine own self, wondrously doth the desire of
 my heart bid me go thither to the ships, into the wide camp of the Achaeans."<lb/>
 <lb/>So spake he, but <action intention="negative" direction="at_someone" setting="private">his
  wife uttered a shrill cry, and spake in answer</action>:"Ah, woe is me, whither now is gone the
 wisdom for the which of old thou wast famed among stranger folk and among them thou rulest? How art
 thou fain to go alone to the ships of the Achaeans to meet the eyes of the man who<lb/>hath slain
 thy sons, many and valiant? Of iron verily is thy heart. For if so be he get thee in his power and
 his eyes behold thee, so savage and faithless is the man, he will neither pity thee nor anywise
 have reverence. Nay, let us now make our lament afar from him we mourn, abiding here in the hall.
 On this wise for him did mighty Fate spin<lb/>with her thread at his birth, when myself did bear
 him, that he should glut swift-footed dogs far from his parents, in the abode of a violent man, in
 whose inmost heart I were fain to fix my teeth and feed thereon; then haply might deeds of requital
 be wrought for my son, seeing in no wise while playing the dastard was he slain of him,<lb/>but
 while standing forth in defence of the men and deep-bosomed women of Troy, with no thought of
 shelter or of flight." Then <action setting="private" intention="positive" direction="at_someone"
  >in answer spake unto her the old man</action>, <character who="Priam" epithet="positive">god-like
  Priam</character>:"Seek not to stay me that am fain to go, neither be thyself a bird of ill-boding
 in my halls; thou shalt not persuade me.<lb/>For if any other of the men that are upon the face of
 the earth had bidden me this, whether of seers that divine from sacrifice or of priests, a false
 thing might we deem it, and turn away therefrom the more; but now—for myself I heard the voice of
 the goddess and looked upon her face—I will go forth, neither shall her word be vain. And if it be
 my fate<lb/>to lie dead by the ships of the brazen-coated Achaeans, so would I have it; forthwith
 let <character who="Achilles">Achilles</character>
 <action direction="at_someone" intention="negative" setting="public">slay me, when once I have
  clasped in my arms my son, and have put from me the desire for wailing</action>."<lb/> He spake,
 and opened the goodly lids of chests, wherefrom he took twelve beauteous robes<lb/>and twelve
 cloaks of single fold, and as many coverlets, and as many white mantles, and therewithal as many
 tunics. And of gold he weighed out and bare forth talents, ten in all, and two gleaming tripods,
 and four cauldrons, and a cup exceeding fair, that the men of Thrace had given him<lb/><action
  setting="public" intention="negative" direction="at_someone">when he went thither on an embassage,
  a great treasure; not even this did the old man spare in his halls, for he was exceeding fain to
  ransom his dear son.</action> Then drave he all the Trojans from out the portico, and chid them
 with words of reviling:"Get ye hence, wretches, ye that work me shame!<lb/>Have ye not also
 lamentation at home, that ye come hither to vex me? Count ye it not enough that <character
  who="Gods" epithet="neutral">Zeus, son of Cronos</character>, hath brought this sorrow upon me,
 that I should lose my son the best of all? Nay, but yourselves too shall know it, for easier shall
 ye be, now he is dead, for the Achaeans to slay.<lb/>But for me, or ever mine eyes behold the city
 sacked and laid waste, may I go down into the house of <character who="Gods">Hades</character>." He
 spake, and plying his staff went among the men, and they went forth from before the old man in his
 haste. Then called he aloud to his sons, chiding Helenus and Paris and goodly Agathon<lb/>and
 Pammon and Antiphonus and Polites, good at the war-cry, and Deiphobus and Hippothous and lordly
 Dius. To these nine the old man called aloud, and gave command:"Haste ye, base children that are my
 shame; would that ye all together in <character who="Hector">Hector</character>'s stead had been
 slain at the swift ships!<lb/>Woe is me, that am all unblest, seeing that I begat sons the best in
 the broad land of Troy, yet of them I avow that not one is left, not godlike Nestor, not Troilus
 the warrior charioteer, not <character who="Hector">Hector</character> that was a god among men,
 neither seemed he as the son of a mortal man, but of a god:<lb/>all them hath Ares slain, yet these
 things of shame are all left me, false of tongue, nimble of foot, peerless at beating the floor in
 the dance, robbers of lambs and kids from your own folk. <action direction="at_someone"
  intention="positive" setting="public">Will ye not make me ready a waggon, and that with speed, and
  lay all these things therein, that we may get forward on our way?</action>"<lb/>
</book>
